<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Count of Gabalis, or, The extravagant mysteries of the Cabalists exposed in five pleasant discourses on the secret sciences / done into English by P.A. Gent., with short animadversions.</title>
            <title>Comte de Gabalis. English</title>
            <author>Villars, abbé de (Nicolas-Pierre-Henri), 1635-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70613</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14099</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12877497e</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12877497</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94889</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70613)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94889)</note>
            <note>Digitized version of: Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 721:8.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Count of Gabalis, or, The extravagant mysteries of the Cabalists exposed in five pleasant discourses on the secret sciences / done into English by P.A. Gent., with short animadversions.</title>
                  <title>Comte de Gabalis. English</title>
                  <author>Villars, abbé de (Nicolas-Pierre-Henri), 1635-1673.</author>
                  <author>Ayres, Philip, 1638-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 183, 11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B.M., Printer to the Cabalistical Society of the Sages, at the sign of the Rosy-Crucian,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>First edition in English.</note>
                  <note>Translation by Philip Ayres of the author's Le comte de Gabalis.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rosicrucians.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94889:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94889:1"/>
            <p>THE Count of <hi>GABALIS:</hi> Or, The Extravagant Myſteries OF
THE Cabaliſts, EXPOSED In Five Pleaſant Diſcourſes On The <hi>Secret
Sciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <q> 
               <p>Quod tanto impendio abſconditur, etiam ſolummodò
demonſtrare, deſtruere eſt.</p> 
               <bibl>Tertullian.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Done into Engliſh, By <hi>P. A.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>With Short Animadverſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. M.</hi> Printer to the
<hi>Cabaliſtical Society</hi> of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> at the Sign of the
<hi>Roſy-Cruſian,</hi> MDCLXXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:94889:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94889:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO MY LORD</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> have alwayes ſhown your ſelf ſo Generous to your
Friends, that I cannot believe, but you will pardon the Liberty I take, in
behalf of one of the beſt of Mine; which is, to beſeech you, to be ſo
kind to him, as to take the pains to read over his Book. I go not about to
engage you in the following Part, which my Friend, the <hi>Author,</hi>
promiſes to publiſh hereafter; ſince I know, theſe <hi>Authors</hi> are
apt to give us large Hopes, of what they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend,<pb facs="tcp:94889:3"/>but often fail. I
told him plainly, That you eſteem it a great Point of Honor, never to ſay
any thing, but what you think; and that he ſhould not flatter himſelf to
imagine, you would put off a Quality ſo rare, and ſo new in the Court, to
ſay his Book is Good, if you find it otherwiſe. But that which I now
deſire of your Lordſhip, and which I humbly beg, you will not deny me, is,
to decide a Difference we have had betwixt us. You ſhould not, <hi>my
Lord,</hi> have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſed to your ſelf, ſuch a prodigious Stock of
Knowledge and Learning, if you have not a mind to be Conſulted, before the
greateſt Doctors. This, Sir, is the Diſpute, which I have had with my
Friend.</p>
            <p>I would have perſwaded him, to have changed the whole Frame of
his Work; for this Drolling way, of carrying it thus on, does not to me, ſeem
proper to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. Theſe Myſteries of the <hi>Cabal</hi> (ſaid I to
him) are ſerious Maters, which many of my Friends do ſeriouſly ſtudy:
They ſhould therefore be Refuted by the Strength of ſolid Arguments. And as
their Errors are generally on things Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; the which, (beſides the
difficulty<pb facs="tcp:94889:3"/>we have, to make a Wiſe Man laugh indeed, at any
Subject what ſo ever) are certainly moſt dangerous to jeſt with: And we
may very well fear, leſt it ſhould caſt a Scandal on our Religion. 'Tis
true, he muſt make a <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> ſpeak like a Saint, or elſe he
improperly manages the Character; and if he does ſo ſpeak like a Saint, he
impoſes on weak Judgments, by this appearance of Sanctity; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably,
ſhall induce Men to entertain a belief of theſe Extravagancies, more than
all his Drolling ſhall be able to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute.</p>
            <p>To this, my Friend anſwer'd, with the ſame Preſumption,
which Authors are accuſtomed to do, when they vindicate their Works: That
though theſe <hi>Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtick Myſteries</hi> be ſo ſerious; yet are
there none but Melancholly Perſons, who addict themſelves to the Study of
them. That ſhould he fall point blank on this Subject, in a Dogmatick Method,
he himſelf would become Ridiculous, for treating ſeriouſly on ſuch
Fooleries: And that he judged it more to the purpoſe, to turn all this
Ridicule on the <hi>Count of Gabalis.</hi> The <hi>Secret Sciences</hi> of the
<hi>Gabal,</hi> are of the number of thoſe <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeras;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:94889:4"/>to
which we give moſt Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, when we diſpute againſt them ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly:
and that we ſhould not therefore undertake to baffle and deſtroy them, but
by jeering. And he being read in the <hi>Fathers,</hi> alledged to me
<hi>Tertullian.</hi> Your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> that underſtands them better
than either He, or I do, may judge whether he has quoted him true or no:
<hi>Multa ſunt riſu digna revinci, ne gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate adorentur.</hi> He ſaid,
That <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> uſed this Excellent Saying, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the
<hi>Valentinians,</hi> who were a kind of very Fanatick
<hi>Roſy-Cruſians,</hi> in his Dayes.</p>
            <p>As to the Devotion, which is almoſt in every part of this Work:
It is an inevitable Neceſſity (ſaid he) that a <hi>Cabaliſt</hi>
ſhould ſpeak of <hi>God.</hi> But then again, it is obſervable in this
Peece, That there is a more inevitable Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, for the keeping up this
<hi>Cabaliſtick Character,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> is never ſpoken of, but
with Extream Reſpect: So that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion cannot receive any Blemmiſh by it;
and weak Judgments ſhall be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuated with it, than the <hi>Lord
Gaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> when they ſuffer themſelves to be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched by this
Extravagant Devotion;<pb facs="tcp:94889:4"/>if the Railery uſed herein, abſtruct not
the Charm.</p>
            <p>By theſe his Reaſons, <hi>(my Lord)</hi> and many others,
which I ſhall forbear to repeat to you (becauſe I am very Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, to
make you of my Party) My Friend pretends, he ought to have writ againſt the
<hi>Cabal,</hi> in this pleaſant Manner. Your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> I hope,
will be pleaſed, to decide this Controverſy. I affirm, It would be moſt
proper, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt the <hi>Cabaliſts,</hi> or
<hi>Roſy-Cruſians,</hi> and againſt all their <hi>Secret Sciences,</hi>
by ſerious and vigorous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments. He ſayes, That Truth is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally
Brisk and Gay; and that ſhe is moſt powerful, when ſhe Laughs: becauſe
one of the Antients, whom without doubt, you know, ſayes, in a certain place,
(which you cannot chuſe, but call to mind, being endued with ſo Faithful a
Memory) <hi>Convenit veritati ridere, quia laetans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He added, That the <hi>Secret Sciences</hi> are dangerous, if we
meddle not with them in ſuch a manner, as may inſpire is with Contempt
againſt them; by pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out their Ridiculous Myſteries, and preventing
the Worlds loſing time,<pb facs="tcp:94889:5"/>in ſearch after them; by ſhewing the
Vanity and End of them, and diſplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Extravagancy. Pray, <hi>(my
Lord)</hi> declare your Sentence, having heard our Reaſons. I ſhall receive
your Deciſion, with that Reſpect, with which you know, I am alwayes obliged
to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips <hi>Servitoriſſimo.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94889:5"/>
            <head>Count <hi>GABALIS:</hi> Or, The Extravagant Myſteries. Of the
<hi>CABALISTS.</hi> OR, ROSY-CRUSIANS. Expoſed in Five Pleaſant
Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on the Secret <hi>Sciences</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="discourse">
               <head>Diſcourſe the Firſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD reſt the Soul of Monſieur the <hi>Count of
Gabalis!</hi> who, as they Write me news, is lately dead of an
<hi>Apoplexy.</hi> Now, the <hi>Cabaliſts</hi> will not fail to ſay, That
this kind of Death<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94889:6"/>is ordinary to thoſe, who impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
manage the Secrets of the <hi>Sages;</hi> and that, ſince the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<hi>Ramundus Lullius</hi> has Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the Sentence in his Laſt Will and
Teſtament, a <hi>Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Angel</hi> has ever been ready to
<hi>ſtrangle</hi> in a Moment, all thoſe who have indiſcreetly Revealed
the <hi>Phyloſophick-Myſteries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let them not ſo raſhly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn this Wiſe Man, without
having better Information of his Conduct. 'Tis true, He has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered all
to me; but not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the <hi>Cabaliſtick</hi> Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpections
requiſite. I muſt do him the right, in giving this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to his
Memory, That he was a great Zealot for the <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> of his Fathers,
the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers;</hi> and that he would have ſuffered the Flames,
rather than have Prophaned the Sanctity of it, by diſcloſing it to any
Unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94889:6"/>Prince, to any Ambitious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or to one that
was Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; three ſorts of People, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated in all Ages by the
Wiſe. By good Fortune, I am no Prince; I have little Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and by the
Sequel of this Diſcourſe, it may be ſeen, that I have a little more
Chaſtity, than a <hi>Sage</hi> needs have. I am end u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Docible Wit,
curious of Knowledge, and Bold enough: I want but a little Melancholly, to make
all thoſe who would blame the <hi>Count of Gabalis,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that he
needed not have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed any thing from me, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard I was a Subject proper
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the Secret Sciences. It is true, that without Melanchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no
great Progreſs can be made therein: But this little Stock of it that I have,
was enough to make me not to be rejected by them. You (has he ſaid a hundred
times<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94889:7"/>to me) have <hi>Saturn</hi> in an Angle, in his Houſe,
and Retrograde; you cannot fail, one of theſe days, of being as Melancholly,
as a <hi>Sage</hi> ought to be: For the Wiſeſt of all Men (as we know in
the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi>) had, as you have, <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the Aſcendant. And
yet, it was never obſerved, that he ever ſo much as once Laughed, in all
his Life-time; ſo powerful was his <hi>Saturn</hi> in him, though it was
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly weaker than yours.</p>
               <p>'Tis then my <hi>Saturn,</hi> and not Monſieur the Count
of<hi>Gabalis,</hi> that the <hi>Virtuoſi</hi> muſt Quarre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with, if I affect more the Divulg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
of their Secrets, than the Practiſing of Them. If the <hi>Stars</hi> do not
their Duty, the <hi>Count</hi> is not in the Fault: And if I have not a
<hi>Soul</hi> Great enough to at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tempt, to become Maſter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nature, to turn the Element<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> up ſide down, to entertain the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94889:7"/>Supreme Intelligences, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the <hi>Daemons,</hi> to
beget <hi>Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants,</hi> to create New Worlds, to ſpeak to <hi>God</hi> in his
High Throne, and to oblige the <hi>Cherubin,</hi> which defends the Entrance of
<hi>Paradice,</hi> to let me come in, and take two or three Turns in his Walks;
'Tis Me, that they muſt blame more or leſs: They muſt not for this,
inſult over the Memory of this Rare Man; and ſay that he is Dead, for
having blabbed all things to me. Is it impoſſible, that amongſt the
wandring Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, he may not have been wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in a Conflict with ſome
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docible <hi>Hobgoblin?</hi> Perchance he is not Dead, but in Appearance;
following the Cuſtom of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> who ſeem to Dye in
one place, and tranſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to another. Be it how it will, I can
never believe, that the Manner where-with he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94889:8"/>his
Treaſures to me, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited any Puniſhment. You ſhall ſee, how all things
paſſed.</p>
               <p>Common Senſe having always made me ſuſpect, that there was
a great deal of Emptineſs in all that which they call <hi>Secret
Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences;</hi> I was never tempted to loſe ſo much time, as to turn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
the Leaves of theſe Books, which Treat of them: But yet, not finding it
reaſonable to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, without knowing why, all thoſe addicting
themſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, who otherwiſe are Wiſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, very Learned for
the moſt part, and Eminent both for the <hi>Gown</hi> and <hi>Sword.</hi> I
took up a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, (that I might avoyd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Unjuſt, and wearying my
ſelf with tedious Reading) of feigning my ſelf a great Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to theſe
Sciences, amongſt all thoſe, whom I could learn were<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94889:8"/>of
that Gang. I had quickly better Succeſs, than I could poſſibly hope for.
Since all theſe Gentlemen, how Myſterious, and how Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſo-ever
they may ſeem to be, deſire nothing more, than to vent their Imaginations,
and the New Diſcoveries, which they pretend to have made in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. In a few
Dayes, I was the Confident of the moſt Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable amongſt them, and
had every Day one or other of them in my Study; which I had on purpoſe
garniſhed with their moſt Phantaſtick Authors. There was never a Learned
<hi>Virtuoſo</hi> of this Kind, but I had Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence with him. In a
word, For my Zeal to this Science, I quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found, that I was well Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
by all. I had for my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, Princes, Great Lords, Gown-Men, Handſom
Ladies, and Unhandſom too; Doctors, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates,<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94889:9"/>Fryars, Nuns:
In fine, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all Ranks and Qualities, Some of them, were for Converſe
with <hi>Angels,</hi> others with <hi>Devils,</hi> others with their
<hi>Genius,</hi> others with <hi>Incubus</hi>'s: Some addicted themſelves to
the Cure of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, ſome to Star-gazing, ſome to the Secrets of
Divinity; and almoſt All, to the <hi>Philoſophers-Stone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They All agreed, that theſe Grand Secrets, and eſpecially,
the <hi>Phyloſophers-Stone,</hi> were hardly to be found out; and that but
very few do attain to them: But they had all in particular, a very good Opinion
of themſelves, to believe, that they were of the Number of the
<hi>Elect.</hi> By good Luck, with infinite Impatiency, the moſt
Conſiderable of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected at this time, the Arrival of a Lord, who was a
great <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſt,</hi> and whoſe Eſtate lyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94889:9"/>the Frontiers of <hi>Poland.</hi> He had promiſed, by Letters to the
Children of <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> to come and Viſit them;
and ſo to paſs from <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England.</hi> I had a
Commiſſion, to write an Anſwer to this Great Man: I ſent him the Scheam
of my Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, that he might judge, if I were capable of aſpiring to the
Supream Wiſdom. My Scheam, and my Letter were ſo Happy, to oblige him to do
me the Honor of Anſwering me; That I ſhould be one of the firſt, that he
would ſee at <hi>Paris;</hi> and that, if <hi>Heaven</hi> did not oppoſe,
there ſhould be nothing wanting in him, to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce me into the Society of
the Wiſe.</p>
               <p>For the well-management of my Good Fortune, I entertain a
Regular Correſpondence with the Illuſtrious <hi>German:</hi> I propoſe to
him, from time to time, great<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94889:10"/>Doubts, as well grounded as I
could, concerning the Harmony of the World, the Numbers of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi>
the Revelations of St. <hi>John,</hi> and the Firſt Chapter of
<hi>Geneſis.</hi> The Greatneſs of the Matter raviſht him! He writ to me
unheard-of Wonders; and I plainly ſaw, that I had to deal with a Man of a
moſt vigorous, and moſt Copious Imagination. I had Threeſcore or
Fourſcore Letters from him, of ſo Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary a Style, that I could not
think of Reading any other thing, even when I was alone in my Study.</p>
               <p>I was Aſtoniſhed one Remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Day, when I ſaw a Man
come in a moſt Excellent Mein; who, Saluting me gravely, ſaid to me in the
<hi>French</hi> Tongue, but in the Accent of a Forreigner: <hi>Adore, my Son;
Adore the moſt Glorious and Great</hi> God <hi>of the</hi> Sages: <hi>And 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94889:10"/>let not thy ſelf be puft up with Pride, that he ſends
to thee one of the Children of Wiſdom, to Conſtitute thee a Fellow of their
Society, and make thee Partaker of the Wonders of his Omnipotency.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſtrange Manner of Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, did upon the ſuddain,
ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize me; and I began, at firſt, to queſtion, whether or no it might
not be ſome Apparition: Nevertheleſs, recovering my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits the beſt I
could, and looking upon him as Civilly as the little Fear I was ſeized with,
could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me. What ever you be (ſaid I to him) whoſe Complement
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>avours not of this World, you do me
a great Honor, in making me this Viſit. But I beſeech you, if you pleaſe,
before I Worſhip this <hi>God</hi> of the <hi>Sages,</hi> let me know, of
what <hi>God,</hi> and what <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> you ſpeak? Do me the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to
ſit down on this Chair,<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94889:11"/>and give your ſelf the Trouble
to tell me, what this <hi>God</hi> is, what theſe <hi>Sages,</hi> this
Company, theſe Wonders of Omnipotency? and after or before all this, What
kind of Creature, I have the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to ſpeak to?</p>
               <p>Sir, You receive me moſt <hi>Sage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,</hi> (ſaid he,
ſmiling, and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chair which I Preſented him) you deſire me on a
ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, to Explain things to you; which, if you pleaſe, I ſhall not
Reſolve to Day. The Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which I made you, are the Words which the
<hi>Sages</hi> uſe at firſt, to thoſe to whom they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to open
their Hearts, and to diſcover their Myſteries. I had thought, that being
ſo Wiſe as you ſeemed to me in your Letters, this Salutation would not
have been unknown to you; and that it would be the moſt pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Complement, that could be<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94889:11"/>made you by the Count of
<hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ah! Sir (cryed I, remembring that I had a Tickliſh Game to
Play) How ſhall I render my ſelf Worthy of ſo much Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Is it
poſſible, that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellenteſt of all Men, ſhould be in my Study?
that the Great <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balis,</hi> ſhould honor me with his Viſit?</p>
               <p>I am the leaſt of the <hi>Sages,</hi> (reply'd he, with a
ſerious Look) and <hi>God,</hi> who diſpenſes the Beams of his Wiſdom,
by Weight and Meaſure, as his Sovereignty plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, has given me but a
ſmall Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, in Compariſon of that which I admire with Aſtoniſhment,
in my Fellows. I hope, that you may equal them, one Day; if I durſt judge of
it by the Scheam of your Nativity, which you did me the Honor to ſend me: But
you give me cauſe to Complain<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94889:12"/>of you, Sir, (added he,
Smiling) in taking me even now for a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>Not for a Spirit, (ſaid I to him) but I proteſt to you, Sir,
that calling to my Remembrance on a ſuddain, what <hi>Cardan</hi> relates of
his Father; That being one day in his Study, he was Viſited by unknown
Perſons, cloathed in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Colours; who entertained him in a pleaſant
Diſcourſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Nature and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.—I underſtand
you (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted the Count,) they were <hi>Sylphes,</hi> of which I ſhall
talk to you here-after: They are a kind of Aerial Subſtances; who
ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times come to Conſult the <hi>Sages,</hi> concerning the Books of
<hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes,</hi> which they do not well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand. <hi>Cardan</hi> was
but a Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb, for Publiſhing that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Subtilties: He had found
thoſe Memories amongſt<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94889:12"/>his Father's Papers, who was one
of Us; and who, ſeeing that his Son was Naturally a Babbler, would Teach him
nothing of what was moſt Conſiderable; but let him puzle his Brains in
Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, by which he was not cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning enough, to prevent his Sons being
Hanged. This Aſs, was the Cauſe of your doing me the Injury, to take me for
a <hi>Sylphe.</hi> Injury (replyed I!) Why Sir, ſhould I be ſo Unfortunate
to—I am not Angry at it, (interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he) ſince you are not oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to know before-hand, that all theſe Elementary Spirits are our Diſciples;
for they are moſt Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, when we will ſtoop ſo low, as to Inſtruct
them; and the leaſt of our <hi>Sages</hi> is more knowing, than all thoſe
Little Gentlemen. But we ſhall talk more at large of this, ſome more
convenient time; It is ſufficient for me to<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94889:13"/>day, that I
have had the Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to ſee you. Endeavor, my Son, to make your ſelf
Worthy of Receiving the <hi>Cabaliſtical</hi> Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations: The Hour of
your Regeneration is come; The Fault is your own, if you become not a
New-Creature. Pray fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him, who only has the Power to Create new
Hearts, to give you one, that may be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the great Things, which I have
to Teach you; and to Inſpire me, not to conceal any thing from you, of our
Myſteries. He then roſe up; and Embracing me, without giving me the
Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to Anſwer him: Farewel, my Son, (purſued he) I muſt go ſee
our Companions, which are at <hi>Paris;</hi> after which, I ſhall Communicate
my News to you. In the mean time, <hi>Watch, Pray, Hope, and be
Silent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94889:13"/>He went out of my Study, in ſaying that;
and I complained of his ſhort Viſit, as I waited on him back, that he had
the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty to leave me ſo quickly, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had let me be ſo Happy, as
to have a Glimpſe of his Light. But having aſſured me with a good Grace,
that I ſhould loſe nothing by this ſuddain Departure; he got up into his
Coach, and left me in a Surprize, which I am not able to Expreſs. I could not
believe my own Eyes, nor my own Ears: I'm ſure, (ſaid I) that this is a Man
of Great Quality; that he hath an Eſtate of Five Thouſand Pounds a Year:
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he appears very Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed. Is it poſſible, that he can
thus ſuffer himſelf to be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with theſe Fooleries? He has talked to
me of theſe <hi>Sylphes,</hi> with great Earneſtneſs: Should he prove a
Sorcerer in the Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot?<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94889:14"/>and, Should I have been Deceived
till now, in believing, that there were no ſuch Things? But, ſuppoſe he
be a Sorcerer, Are there alſo ſome of them ſo Devout, as this Man appears
to be?</p>
               <p>I could not Comprehend any thing of all this: Nevertheleſs, I
reſolved to ſee the End of it; though I well enough fore-ſaw, that he had
ſome ſet Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to handle; and that the <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> which
agitated him, was a great Moraliſt, and a Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="discourse">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94889:14"/>
               <head>Diſcourſe the Second.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Count</hi> was pleaſed to allow me all the Night in
Prayer: And in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by Break of Day, he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted me by a Note, that
he would come to my Houſe by Eight of the Clock; and that, if I pleaſed, we
might go and take the Air together. I wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for him; he came; and after
Reciprocal Civilities: Let us go (ſaid he to me) to ſome Place, where we
may be free together, and where no Body may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our Diſcourſe.
<hi>Ruel</hi> (ſaid I to him) ſeems to be a Place very Pleaſant, and very
Solitary. Let us thither then, (reply'd he:) So up we get into the Coach; and
all the way, I obſerv'd my New<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94889:15"/>Maſter. I never ſaw in
any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo great Marks of Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as appeared in all his
Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures. He had a Spirit more mild, calm, and free, than me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought a
Sorcerer could have. All his Countenance, and Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, was not as of a Man,
whoſe Conſcience could reproach him with any thing that was Black; and I
was in a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Impatience, till I ſhould ſee him enter upon the
Matter: Not being able to comprehend, how a Man, who ſeemed to me ſo
Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, and ſo Accompliſht in all things elſe, ſhould imploy his
Wits in theſe Ridiculous Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, with which I knew him the Day before,
to be infected. He diſcourſed to me of Policy moſt Divinely; and was
infinit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed, to hear that I had read what <hi>Plato</hi> has writ of
it. You will have need enough of<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94889:15"/>all that, one Day, (ſaid
he to me), a little more, than you think you ſhall: And if we agree together
to day, it is not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, but that in a ſmall time, you may put in
Practice theſe <hi>Sage</hi> Maxims. By this time, we were got to
<hi>Ruel,</hi> and went into the Garden; the <hi>Count</hi> vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing to
Admire the Beauty of it, and walked ſtraight to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth.</p>
               <p>He ſeeing, that we were as free from Company, as he could
deſire: I beſeech, (cry'd he, lifting up his Eyes and Hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
Heaven) I <hi>beſeech</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Wiſdom, that I may be Inſpired in
ſuch a manner, as that I may not conceal any of theſe inexpreſſible
Truths from you: How Happy ſhall you be, my Son, if Heaven has the
Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to put thoſe Diſpoſitions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Soul, which the High 
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94889:16"/>Myſteries require of you! You are about to Learn, how to
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Nature; <hi>God</hi> alone, ſhall be your Maſter; and the
<hi>Sages</hi> only, ſhall be your Equals: The Supream Intelligences ſhall
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it a Glory, to obey your Deſires: The <hi>Devils</hi> ſhall not
dare to approach, where you are; Your Voyce ſhall make them tremble, in the
moſt profound Caves of their Abyſs. And all the Inviſible People, who
inhabit the Four Elements, ſhall account themſelves Happy, to be the
Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of your Pleaſures. I A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore thee, O Great <hi>God!</hi> for
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Crowned <hi>Man</hi> with ſo much Glory, and for having
Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>him</hi> the Soveraign Monarch over all the Works of thy
Hands! Do you feel, my Son, (added he, turning himſelf towards me) Do you
feel this Heroick Ambition, which is the certain Character<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94889:16"/>of the Children of <hi>wiſdom?</hi> Dare you deſire, to Serve
nothing but <hi>God</hi> only; and to Rule over all Things, which is not of
<hi>God?</hi> Have you comprehended, what it is to be a Man? And, Do you not
deteſt the being of a Slave, ſince you were Born to be a Soveraign? And if
you have theſe Noble Thoughts, as the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of your Nativity ſuffers me
not to doubt; conſider <hi>ſoberly,</hi> if you can have the Courage, and
Strength, to Renounce all Things, which may be an Obſtacle to you, in the
attaining that Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to which you were Born? He ſtopt there, and
beheld me ſtedfaſtly; as attending my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, or as if he were reading
my Heart.</p>
               <p>How much ſoever the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Diſcourſe had made
me hope, that we ſhould enter preſently upon the Matter; ſo 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94889:17"/>much the more was I become deſperate at what he had
laſt ſaid. The word <hi>RENO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NCE,</hi> ſo affrighted me, that I
queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether or no he was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to propoſe to me, the
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of my <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</hi> So that, not
knowing how to get out of theſe Streights: Renounce, (ſaid I to him!) Why,
Sir, need I Renounce any thing? Truly, (reply'd he) there is need enough; and
ſo much need, that we muſt begin with that Point firſt: I know not
whether or no you can reſolve upon it; but I know very well, that
<hi>Wiſdom</hi> does not inhabit a Body ſubject to Sin, no more, than it
enters into a Soul, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed with Error or Malice. The
<hi>Sages</hi> will never admit you into their Society, if you do not Renounce
from this very preſent, a Thing which cannot ſtand in<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94889:17"/>Competition with Wiſdom. You muſt (added he, ſtooping down, and
whiſpering in my Ear) <hi>You must Renounce all Carnal Commerce with
Women.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could not forbear breaking out into a fit of Laughter at this
pleaſant Propoſition. Well Sir, (cryed I!) you have quitted me for a very
ſmall Matter: I had thought, that you would have propoſed to me ſome
ſtrange Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation; but ſince it is only <hi>Women,</hi> I aſſure
you, that Work is long ſince done. I am very Chaſt <hi>(God be
thanked!)</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, Sir, in regard that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was
Wiſer than I, it may be, ſhall ever be, and that all his Wiſdom could not
hinder him from being Corrupted by them. I beſeech you tell me, what
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient you Gentlemen take, to keep you from this Sex? And, what
Inconvenience there would<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94889:18"/>be, if in the <hi>Philoſophers
Paradice,</hi> every <hi>Adam</hi> had his <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There you ask great Matters, (reply'd he, conſulting with
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if he ſhould Anſwer my Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or not) but yet ſince I
ſee, that you deſert <hi>Women</hi> without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Trouble, I ſhall tell
you one of the Reaſons, which have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged the <hi>Sages</hi> to impoſe
this Condition on their Diſciples; and from thence you will know in what
Ignorance all thoſe Live, who are not of our Number.</p>
               <p>When you ſhall be enrolled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Children of
<hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> and that your Eyes ſhall be Fortifyed by the uſe of
our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Medicine; you ſhall imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly diſcover, that the
<hi>Elements</hi> are inhabited by moſt Perfect Creatures; from the Knowledge
and Commerce of whom, the Sin of the Unfortunate <hi>Adam,</hi> has ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
all his too Unhappy Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94889:18"/>This immenſe Space,
which is between the Earth, and the <hi>Heavens,</hi> has more Noble
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, than <hi>Birds</hi> and <hi>Flyes:</hi> This vaſt Ocean has
alſo other Troops, beſides <hi>Dolphins</hi> and <hi>Whales:</hi> The
Profoundity of the Earth, is not only for <hi>Moles;</hi> And the
<hi>Element</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> (more No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than the other Three) was not
made to be Unprofitable and Voyd.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Air</hi> is full of an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Multitude of People,
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Human Shape, ſomewhat Fierce in appearance, but Tract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able upon
experience: Great Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the Sciences, Subtil, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious to the
<hi>Sages,</hi> and Enemies to Sots and Ignorants. Their Wives, and their
Daughters have a kind of Maſculine Beauty, ſuch as we deſcribe the
<hi>Amazons</hi> to have. How Sir, (cryed I!) Would you perſwade me, that
theſe<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94889:19"/>Fiends you ſpeak of, are Marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Be not ſo Fierce, my Son, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he) for ſo ſmall a
Matter. Believe whatſoever I tell you, to be Solid and true. <hi>I am mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
known nothing to you,</hi> but the Principles of the Antient <hi>Cabal;</hi>
and there needs nothing more to juſtify them, than that you ſhould believe
your own Eyes: But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with a Meek Spirit, the Light which <hi>God</hi>
ſends you by my Interpoſition. Forget all that you may have heard touching
theſe Matters, in the Schools of the Ignorants: whereat you will be
diſpleaſed, when you ſhall be convinced by Experience, and be obliged to
diſown, what former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you had a good Opinion of to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Liſten then to the End; and know, that the <hi>Seas</hi> and
<hi>Rivers</hi> are Inhabited, as well as the <hi>Air:</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:94889:19"/>The Antient <hi>Sages</hi> have called theſe kind of People
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndians</hi> or <hi>Nymphs.</hi> They have but few Males amongſt them;
but the Women are there in great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: Their Beauty is marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; and the
Daughters of Men have nothing in them, compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to theſe.</p>
               <p>The Earth is filled almoſt to the Center with <hi>Gnomes</hi>
or <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes;</hi> a People of ſmall Stature; the Guardians of
Treaſures, of Mines, and of Precious Stones. They are Ingenious, Friends of
Men, and eaſie to be command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. They furniſh the Children of the
<hi>Sages</hi> with as much Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as they have need of; and never ask any
other Reward of their Services, than the Glory of being Commanded. The
<hi>Gno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mides</hi> or Wives of theſe <hi>Gnomes</hi> or <hi>Pharyes,</hi> are
Little, but very<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94889:20"/>Handſom; and their Habit mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellouſly
Curious.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Salamanders,</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Region
of <hi>Fire:</hi> They ſerve the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> but they ſeek not
for their Company with any great Eagerneſs; and their Wives and Daughters
will rarely be ſeen. They do wiſely, (interrupted I) and for my ſhare, I
ſhall excuſe their Appearing to me. Why
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid the <hi>Count?</hi>) Why, Sir, (reply'd I?) What
Buſineſs can I have, to Converſe with ſo ugly a Creature as a
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander,</hi> be it either Male or Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male? You are miſtaken,
(an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered he) that is the <hi>Idea,</hi> which the ignorant Painters and
Sculp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have given them: The Wives of the <hi>Salamanders</hi> are Fair;
nay, rather more Fair, than all others, ſeeing they are of a purer Element.
But I forbear to ſpeak more of that, and ſhall give <pb n="31" facs="tcp:94889:20"/>but
a ſlight Deſcription of theſe People; becauſe you ſhall ſee them
your ſelf, at your Leaſure; and that very eaſily too, if you have the
Curioſity for it. You ſhall ſee their Habits, their Diet, their Manners,
their Policy, and their Admirable Laws. You will be Charmed more, with the
Beauty of their Wit, than that of their Body: Yet you cannot chooſe, but be
grieved for theſe poor Wretches, when they ſhall tell you, That their
<hi>Soul</hi> is Mortal; and that they have no Hope of enjoying Eternal
Happyneſs, and of the Supreme Being, which they acknowledge, and
Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly adore. They will tell us, That being Compoſed of the moſt
pure Parts of the <hi>Elements,</hi> which they inhabit; and not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in
them any contrary Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, ſeeing they are made but of one
<hi>Element,</hi> they Dye not but<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94889:21"/>after many Ages: But
Alas! What is ſuch a Time, in reſpect of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity? They muſt Eternally
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve into their Nothing. This Conſideration does ſorely afflict them;
and we have Trouble e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to comfort them concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
               <p>Our Fathers, the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> ſpeaking to
<hi>God</hi> Face to Face, complained to him of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happyneſs of theſe
People; and <hi>God,</hi> whoſe Mercy is without bounds, revealed to them,
that it was not impoſſible to find out a Remedy for this Evil. He
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired them, that by the ſame Means as Man, by the Alliance which he
Contracted with <hi>God,</hi> has been made Partakers of the Divinity: The
<hi>Sylphs,</hi> the <hi>Gnomes,</hi> the <hi>Nymphs,</hi> and the
<hi>Salamanders,</hi> by the Alliance which they might Contract with Man, might
be made Partakers of Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94889:21"/>So a She-<hi>Nymph,</hi>
or a <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phide</hi> becomes Immortal, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the Bleſſing to
which we aſpire, when they ſhall be ſo happy as to be married to a
<hi>Sage;</hi> a <hi>Gnome,</hi> or a <hi>Sylphe</hi> ceaſes to be Mortal,
from the moment that he Eſpouſes one of our Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>Hence aroſe the Error of the former Ages, of
<hi>Tertullian,</hi> of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> of <hi>Lactantius, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,
Clemens Alexandrinus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenagoras</hi> the Chriſtian
<hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher;</hi> and generally, of all the Writers of that time They
had learnt, that theſe <hi>Elementary Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> had endeavored a
Commerce with Maids; and they have from thence imagined, that the Fall of the
<hi>Angels</hi> had not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, but for the Love which they were touched
with after <hi>Women</hi> Certain <hi>Gnomes,</hi> deſirous of becoming
Immortal, had a<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94889:22"/>mind to gain the good Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our
<hi>Daughters;</hi> and had brought abundance of Precious Stones, of which they
are the Natural <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uardians: And
theſe Authors, relying on the Book of <hi>Enoch,</hi> which they
miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, thought that it was the Attempt which theſe Amorous
<hi>Angels</hi> had offered to the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity of our Wives. In the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,
theſe <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> begat Famous <hi>Gyants,</hi> by
making themſelves beloved by the Daughters of Men: And the ill Cabaliſts,
<hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Philo,</hi> (as all the <hi>Jews</hi> are ignorant)
and after them all the other <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors,</hi> which I have juſt now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
as well as <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius,</hi> have ſaid, that they were
<hi>Angels;</hi> and have not known, that they were the <hi>Sylphes,</hi> and
other People of the <hi>Elements;</hi> that under the Name of the
<hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> 
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:94889:22"/>of <hi>Elohim,</hi> are
diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the <hi>Children</hi> of Men. Likewiſe, that which
the <hi>Sage</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> has had the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty to leave
undetermined, touching the Purſuits which thoſe called <hi>Faunes</hi> or
<hi>Satyrs,</hi> made after the <hi>Africans</hi> of his time, is cleared by
that which I have now alledged, of the Deſire which all theſe
<hi>Elementary</hi> Inhabitants have, of Allying themſelves to Men; as the
only means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Immortality which they have not.</p>
               <p>No, no! Our <hi>Sages</hi> have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Err'd ſo, as to
attribute the Fall of the firſt <hi>Angels,</hi> to their Love of
<hi>Women,</hi> no more than they have put Men under the Power of the
<hi>Devil;</hi> by imput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Adventures of the <hi>Nymphs</hi> and
<hi>Sylphs</hi> to him, of which the <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> ſpeak ſo
largely. There was nothing Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94889:23"/>in all that. They were
the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> which endeavoured to become Immortal. Their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
Purſuits, far enough from being able to ſcandalize the
<hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> have appeared ſo Juſt to us, that we are all
reſolved by common Conſent, utterly to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>Women;</hi> and
intirely to give our ſelves to the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talizing of the <hi>Nymphs</hi> and
<hi>Sylphs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good Lord, (cryed I!) What do I hear? Was there ever ſuch
marvellous F— Yes, my Son, (interrupted the <hi>Count</hi>) Admire the
marvellous Felicity of the <hi>Sages!</hi> Inſtead of <hi>Women,</hi> whoſe
fading Beauty paſs away in a ſhort time, and are followed with horrible
Wrinkles and Ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> enjoy Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which
never wax old, and whom they have the glory to make Immortal. Gueſs at the 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94889:23"/>Love and Acknowledgment of theſe inviſible
Miſtreſſes; and with what Ardor they ſtrive to pleaſe the Charitable
<hi>Philoſopher,</hi> who Labours to Immortalize them.</p>
               <p>Ah! Sir, (cryed I once again) I Renounce—. Yes, my Son,
(purſued he, without giving me the Leaſure to finiſh) Renounce the fading
Pleaſures, which are to be had with <hi>Women;</hi> the Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt amongſt
them all, is Loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, in reſpect of the Homelieſt <hi>Sylphide:</hi> No
Diſpleaſure ever follows our <hi>Sage</hi> Embraces. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable
Ignorants! How ſhould you complain, that ye have not the Power to taſt of
the <hi>Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phick</hi> Pleaſures!</p>
               <p>Miſerable <hi>Count de Gabalis,</hi> (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted I, in an
Accent mixed with Choler and Compaſſion!) Will you give me leave to tell
you at laſt, That I Renounce this<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94889:24"/>ſenſeleſs
Wiſdom; That I find this Viſionary <hi>Philoſophy</hi> very Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous:
That I deteſt the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Embraces, which make you affect theſe
Phantaſms; and that I tremble for you, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that ſome one of theſe
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Sylphides</hi> does not hurry you to <hi>Hell,</hi> in the
middle of your Tranſports and Raptures; and for fear, leſt ſo honeſt a
Man as you, ſhould not perceive the End of your fooliſh <hi>Chymerick</hi>
Zeal, and ſhould not Repent of ſo great a Crime.</p>
               <p>Oh! Oh! (anſwered he, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyling two or three Paces back, and
earneſtly looking upon me with an Angry Countenance) Miſchief light on thy
indocible Spirit! His Action, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, affrighted me; but it was
yet worſe, when I perceived, that going further from me, he drew out of his
Pocket a Paper; which<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94889:24"/>I could eaſily ſee at that
diſtance, to be full of Characters; yet I could not well diſcern it. He
read them gravely, and ſpake low. I gueſſed, that he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking ſome
Spirit for my Ruin, and Repented me more than a little for my inconſiderate
Zeal. If I eſcape this adventure, (ſaid I) I'le never have to do with a
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balist</hi> more. I fixed my eyes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as upon a Judge that was
ready to condemn me to Death; When at laſt, I perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that his looks
became ſerene. <hi>'Tis hard</hi> (ſaid he, ſmiling, and coming towards
me again) <hi>'Tis hard for you to kick against the Pricks.</hi> You are a
Veſſel of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. <hi>Heaven</hi> has ordained you, to be the greateſt
<hi>Cabaliſt</hi> of your Age. Behold the Scheme of your Nativity, which
cannot fail. If it be not now, and that too by my means, 'twill be a 
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94889:25"/>great wonder, as appears by this <hi>Saturn
retrograde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas, Sir, (ſaid I to him) if I muſt become a <hi>Sage,</hi>
it will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be but by the means of the Great <hi>Gabalis:</hi> But to deal
free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you, I am affraid, that you will find it a difficult mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to
bend me to this <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical</hi> Mode. It ſeems (continued he) that
you ſhould be but ill read in <hi>Phyſicks,</hi> that cannot be perſwaded
of the exiſtance of theſe People? I know not, (anſwered I) but I cannot
Imagine that theſe can be any things elſe but Fiends diſguiſed. Do you
ſtill (ſaid he) rather believe your own Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeys, than Natural Reaſon?
than <hi>Plato, Pythagorus, Celſus, Pſellus, Proclus, Porphyrius,
Jam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus, Plotinus, Triſmegiſtus, Nol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Dorneus, Fludd;</hi> than the
great <hi>Philippus Aureolus Theophra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus Bombſt Paracelſus de
Honein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem;</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:94889:25"/>and than all our Society?</p>
               <p>I would believe you (Anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I) as ſoon, nay ſooner,
than all theſe: But, Dear Sir, could you not ſo order the buſineſs with
the reſt of your ſociety, that I might not be obliged to have Carnal
knowledge of theſe Elementary Ladies? Away, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, (reply'd he) you have your
own Liberty, without doubt; for no-body loves, unleſs he has a mind to it.
Few of the <hi>Sages</hi> have been able to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from their
charms: But it has been obſerved, that ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving themſelves
wholly and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely for great things, (as you will know in time) would never
do this honor to the Nymphs. I will be then of this number, (ſaid I:) But yet
neither can I reſolve to looſe time about the ceremonies which I have heard
a <hi>Prelate</hi> ſay, muſt be practized<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94889:26"/>by thoſe who
mean to converſe with their Genius's. This <hi>Prelate</hi> knew not what he
ſaid, (ſaid the <hi>Count;</hi>) for you ſhall ſee ere long, that there
are no Genius's there; and beſides, that never any <hi>Sage</hi> employed
either Ceremonies or Superſtition for the familiarity of the Genius's, no
more than for the People of whom we ſpeak.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Cabaliſtes</hi> do nothing, but by the Principles of
Nature: And if there are ſometimes found in our Books certain ſtrange
words, characters, or Fumigations, 'tis but to conceal the
<hi>Philoſophical</hi> Principles from the Ignorant. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the Simplicity
of Nature, in all her moſt marvellous Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations! And in this Simplicity, a
Harmony, and Agreement ſo great, ſo juſt, and ſo neceſſary, that it
will make you return back, in deſpite of your ſelf, from your 
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:94889:26"/>weak Imaginations. That which I am now going about to tell
you, we teach thoſe of our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, which we will not let al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
enter into the Sanctuary of Nature; and whom we will nevertheleſs, not
utterly deprive of the Society of the Elementary People, meerly out of the
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion which we have for theſe poor wretches.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Salamanders</hi> (as you have already, perhaps,
comprehended) are Compoſed of the moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Parts of the
<hi>Sphaere</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> conglobated and organiz'd by the Action of
the Univerſal <hi>Fire,</hi> (concerning which, I ſhall one day entertain
you further) ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, becauſe it is principal of all the Motions of
Nature.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sylphes</hi> in like manner, are Compoſed of the
pureſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes of the Air: The <hi>Nymphs,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:94889:27"/>of the
moſt delicate parts of the Water; and the <hi>Gnomes</hi> of the
ſubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt parts of the Earth. There was a great Proportion betwixt
<hi>Adam,</hi> and theſe ſo perfect Creatures; becauſe they being
compoſed of that which was moſt pure in the four Elements; He comprehended
the perfections of theſe four ſorts of People, and was their Natural King.
But ſince the time that his ſin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated him into the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of
the Elements, (as you ſhall ſee hereafter) the Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was diſordered,
and there was no more proportion, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing become <hi>Impure,</hi> and
<hi>Dull,</hi> in reſpect of theſe ſubſtances ſo pure and ſo
ſubtil. What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for this evil? How ſhall we remount this throne, and
recover this loſt Soveraignty? O Nature! Why do they ſtudy thee ſo
little? Do you not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94889:27"/>my Son, with what
ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity nature can render to man the Goods which he has loſt?</p>
               <p>Alas! Sir (reply'd I) I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ignorant in all theſe
ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, you ſpeak of. And yet (purſued he) it is very eaſie to
become knowing in them.</p>
               <p>If we would recover that Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire over the Salamanders: we muſt
purifie and exalt the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Fire which is in us, and raiſe up the tone
of this ſlackned ſtring, we need do <hi>no more,</hi> but concenter the
Fire of the World by Concave Mirrours in a Globe of Glaſs. And herein, is
that great piece of Art which all the Ancients have ſo Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
concealed, and which the Divine <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> has diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
There is formed in this Globe a Solar powder, which being purified by it ſelf
from the<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94889:28"/>Mixture of other Elements; and being prepared
according to art, becomes in a very little time, Soveraignly proper to exalt
the Fire which is in us, and make us become (according to our Phraſe) of a
Fiery Nature. From that time the inhabitants of the Sphere of Fire become our
inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, and raviſht to ſee our mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Harmony re-ſtabliſht, and
that we once more approach to them: They have all the kindneſs for us which
they have for their own <hi>Species,</hi> all the reſpect which they owe to
the Image and to the Lieutenant of their Creator; and all the concern which may
make evident in them, the deſire of obtaining by us, the immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which
they want. 'Tis true, that as they are more ſubtil than thoſe of the other
Elements, they live a very long time, ſo they are not very forward, to
impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94889:28"/>the Sages to make them immortal. You may
accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date your ſelf with one of theſe, if the averſion which you have
witneſſed to me laſt not with you to the end: perchance, ſhe will never
ſpeak to you of that which you fear ſo much.</p>
               <p>It will not be ſo with the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> the
<hi>Gnomes,</hi> and the <hi>Nymphs;</hi> For they living a leſs time, have
more need of us: and ſo their famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity is more eaſie to obtain. You
need but ſhut up a glaſs fill'd with Conglobated Air, Water, or Earth, and
expoſe it to the Sun for a month; Then ſeparate the Element according to
art, which is very eaſie to do, if it be Earth or Water. 'Tis a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous
thing to ſee, what a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue every one of theſe purified Elements have to
attract the <hi>Nymphes, Sylphs,</hi> and <hi>Gnomes.</hi> In taking but never
ſo little, everyday,<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94889:29"/>for about a month together, one
ſhall ſee in the Air the volant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique of the <hi>Sylphs;</hi> The
<hi>Nymphes</hi> come in ſhoales up the Rivers, and the Guardians of
Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, preſenting you with their riches. Thus without Characters,
without Ceremonies, without Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous words, you become abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Maſter
over all theſe people. They require no worſhip of the <hi>Sages,</hi>
ſince they know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that he is nobler than they. Thus venerable
Nature teaches her Children how to repair the Elements by the Elements. Thus is
Harmony re-eſtabliſhed. Thus man recovers his natural Empire, and can do
all things in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, without <hi>Daemon,</hi> or unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful art. Thus
you ſee, my Son, that the <hi>Sages</hi> are more innocent than you thought.
You ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to me—</p>
               <p>I admire Sir (ſaid I) and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94889:29"/>to fear,
that you will make me become a Chymiſt. Ah! God preſerve thee from that, my
Child, (cryed he) 'Tis not to theſe fooleries that your Nativity deſigns
you, I will warrant you on the contrary, from being troubled about that: I told
you already, That the <hi>Sages</hi> ſhew not theſe things, but to thoſe
whom they will not admit into their Society. You ſhall have all theſe
Advantages, and others infinitely more Glorious, and more Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, by wayes
cleerly more <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical.</hi> I had not deſcribed theſe Methods
to you, but to let you ſee the Innocence of this <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi> and
to take you out of theſe <hi>Panick</hi> Fears.</p>
               <p>I thank God, Sir, (anſwered I) I am not at preſent, in any
ſuch Fear as I was even now. And although I do not yet reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the
Accommodation, which you<pb n="50" facs="tcp:94889:30"/>poſe to me with the
<hi>Salamanders;</hi> I cannot refrain from having the Curioſity to learn how
you have diſcovered, that theſe <hi>Nymphs,</hi> and theſe
<hi>Sylphs</hi> Dye? Truly (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed he) they tell us ſo, and we ſee them
Dye. How, (ſaid I) Can you ſee them Dye, and yet your Commerce renders them
Immortal? That would be well, (pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ued he) if the Number of the <hi>Sages</hi> equalled the Number of
theſe <hi>People:</hi> Beſides that, there are many amongſt them, who
rather chooſe to Dye, than ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard by becoming Immortal, the being ſo
unhappy as they ſee the <hi>Devils</hi> are. And 'tis the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi>
who Inſpired them with theſe Opinions; for there is no Miſchief, which he
doth not do, to hinder theſe poor Creatures from becoming Immortal by our
Allyance. Inſomuch, that I look upon it, (and ſo ought you, my
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94889:30"/>Son) as a moſt pernicious Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and a Motion of
very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Charity, to have this Averſion which you ſhew to it.</p>
               <p>Moreover, as concerning their Death, of which you ſpeak: What
was it that obliged the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> to ſay, That all thoſe
who ſpeak Oracles, were Mortal, as well as he; as <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrius</hi>
reports? And, What think you, was the meaning of that Voyce, which was heard on
all the <hi>Coaſt</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſtruck ſo great a Terror
into all thoſe who were upon the <hi>Sea? THE GREAT</hi> PAN <hi>IS
DEAD!</hi> They were the People of the Air; who gave notice to the People of
the <hi>Water,</hi> that the Chiefeſt, and moſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of all the
<hi>Sylphs,</hi> was newly Dead.</p>
               <p>At that time, when this Voyce was heard, (ſaid I to him) I
<hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> that the World worſhipped<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94889:31"/>
                  <hi>Pan,</hi> and the <hi>Nymphs:</hi> And that theſe Gentlemen,
whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce you are Preaching of to me, were the <hi>Falſe Gods</hi> of
the <hi>Heathens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, my Son, (reply'd he) The <hi>Sages</hi> have alwayes
been of that opinion, That the <hi>Devil</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had the Power to make
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Worſhipped. He is too Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, and too Weak, ever to have had
this Pleaſure, and this Authority. But he has been able to perſwade the
<hi>Elementary Hosts,</hi> to ſhew themſelves to Men, and make men erect
Temples to them; and by the Natural Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, which every one has o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the
<hi>Element</hi> which he inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, they trouble the <hi>Air,</hi> and the
<hi>Sea,</hi> ſet the Earth in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion, and diſpenſe the Fire of
<hi>Heaven,</hi> according to their Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour: Inſomuch, that they had no great
trouble to be taken for<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94889:31"/>
                  <hi>Deities,</hi> ſo long as the
Sovereign Being differ'd the Salvation of the World. But the <hi>Devil</hi>
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver received all the Advantage of his Malice, which he hoped he ſhould:
For it has happened from thence, that <hi>Pan,</hi> the <hi>Nymphs,</hi> and
the reſt of the <hi>Elementary People,</hi> having found the Means of
changing this Commerce of Worſhip, into a Commerce of Love; (for you may
remember, that amongſt the Antients, <hi>Pan</hi> was the King of thoſe
<hi>Gods</hi> whom they called <hi>Incubuſes,</hi> and who alwayes
earneſtly ſought the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of Maids) many <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> have
eſcaped the <hi>Devil,</hi> and ſhall never Burn in <hi>Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not well underſtand you, Sir, (ſaid I.) You have not
mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, to underſtand me, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he, ſmiling, and in a jeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Tone.) Behold what you paſs over! and likewiſe, what<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94889:32"/>your Doctors paſs over, who know not what theſe Excellent
<hi>Phyſicks</hi> mean! Behold the Great Myſtery of all this Part of
<hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,</hi> which concerns the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> and which will
take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way (if you have but never ſo little Love for your ſelf) this
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnance to <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi> which you have witneſſed to me this
Day! Know then, my Son; and go not about to divulge this great <hi>Arcanum</hi>
to any unworthy Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Know, that as the <hi>Sylphs</hi> acquire an
Immortal Soul, by the Allyance which they Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract with the Men who are
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated; ſo alſo, the Men who have no right to Eternal Glory:
Thoſe Miſerable Wretches, whoſe Immortality is but a lamentable
Advantage, for whom the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> was not ſent—</p>
               <p>Then, you Gentlemen of the <hi>Cabal,</hi> are
<hi>Janſeniſts</hi> likewiſe, (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94889:32"/>I?) We
know not what that is, my Child, (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded he, ſomewhat Angryly) and we
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>corn to inform our ſelves,
wherein conſiſts the different Sects, and divers Religions, with which the
Ignorant puzzle their Heads. We keep to the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Religion of our Fathers,
the <hi>Philoſophers;</hi> wherein 'tis very neceſſary, that I inſtruct
you. But to come again to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Theſe Men, whoſe ſad
Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality is nothing but an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Misfortune; The unhappy Children, whom
the Sovereign Father has neglected, have alſo this Recourſe, that they may
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Mortal, by Contracting an Allyance with theſe <hi>Elementary</hi>
People. So that you ſee, the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> hazard nothing for Eternity. If
they are Predeſtinated, they have the Pleaſure to carry with them to Heaven
(in quitting the<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94889:33"/>Priſon of this Body) the
<hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phide,</hi> or <hi>Nymph,</hi> which they have Immortalized: And if
they be not Predeſtinated, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of the <hi>Nymph</hi> renders their
<hi>Soul</hi> Mortal, and delivers them from the Horrors of the Second Death.
So the <hi>Devil</hi> ſaw all the <hi>Pagans</hi> eſcape, who Allyed
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the <hi>Nymphs:</hi> And ſo the <hi>Sages,</hi> or Friends
of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> when <hi>God</hi> Inſpires us to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to any
one, the Four <hi>Elementary Secrets,</hi> (which I have now been teaching you)
free themſelves from the Peril of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Damned.</p>
               <p>Without Lying, Sir, (cryed I, not daring to put him again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
an ill Humor; and finding it requiſite to defer the telling him plainly my
Opinion, till I ſhould have diſcovered all the Secrets of his
<hi>Cabal,</hi> which I judged by this Glimps, muſt needs be very full 
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94889:33"/>of Pleaſure and Divertiſement:) Without Lying, You
advance Wiſdom to a great Height! And you had reaſon to tell me, That this
ſurpaſſed all our Doctors: And I believe, that this likewiſe paſſes
all our Magiſtrates too: And that, if they could diſcover who thoſe were,
that ecſaped the <hi>Devil</hi> by this means, (as Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance is very
Unjuſt) they would engage in the <hi>Devil</hi>'s In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, againſt
theſe Fugitives, and make a ſtrong Party for him.</p>
               <p>Yes, It is for that, (purſued the <hi>Count</hi>) that I have
ſo ſtrictly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you; and do again com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, to keep
Religiouſly this Secret. Your Judges are ſtrange Perſons! They Condemn a
moſt innocent Action, as a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Crime. What a Barbarity was it, to Burn
thoſe two <hi>Prieſts,</hi> which the Prince of <hi>Miranda</hi> 
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:94889:34"/>ſayes he knew of, who had each of them his
<hi>Sylphide,</hi> for the ſpace of Forty Years! What an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>human thing was
it, to put <hi>Joan Herviller</hi> to death, for having la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured Six and Forty
Years, to Immortalize a <hi>Gnome!</hi> And, What a piece of Ignorance was that
of <hi>Bodin,</hi> to repreſent her as a <hi>Witch;</hi> that from thence he
might take advantage to Authorize popular Errors, touching pretended
<hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers;</hi> in a Book as Impertinent, as his <hi>Common-Wealth</hi> is
Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
               <p>But it is late; and I do not conſider, that you have not yet
Dined. 'Tis your ſelf, that you mean, Sir, (ſaid I) for as for my part, I
could liſten to you till to Morrow, without Inconvenience. For me! Alas!
(reply'd he, Laughing, and walking towards the Gate) 'Tis eaſily ſeen, that
you underſtand but little, what<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94889:34"/>
                  <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> is.
The <hi>Sages</hi> Eat but for their Pleaſure, and never for Neceſſity. I
had a quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Idea</hi> of Wiſdom, (anſwered I;) I had thought,
that you Wiſe-men ſhould never Eat but to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy Nature. You are
abuſed, (ſaid the <hi>Count.</hi>) How long think you, that our
<hi>Sages</hi> can ſubſiſt without Eating? How can I tell? (anſwered I)
<hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> you know, Faſted forty Dayes: You
<hi>Sages,</hi> I make no doubt, may do it ſome few Dayes leſs. What a
great piece of Buſineſs would that be? (Replyed he) The moſt Wiſe Man
that ever was, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, the almoſt Adorable <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus,</hi>
affirms, that he has ſeen many of the <hi>Sages</hi> Faſt Twenty Years,
without Eating any thing whatſoever. He himſelf, before he attained to the
Monarchy of Wiſdom, whereof we have juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſented him the Scepter:
He,<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94889:35"/>I ſay, would undertake to Live many Years without
Eating, by taking but half a Scruple of his Solar Quinteſcence. And if you
would have the Pleaſure to make any one Live without Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, you need do
no more, but prepare the Earth, as I told you it muſt be prepared, for the
So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of the <hi>Gnomes:</hi> This Earth applyed to the <hi>Navle,</hi> and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed when it is too dry, will cauſe any one to Live without Eating or
Drinking and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any trouble.</p>
               <p>And the uſe of this
<hi>Catholick-Cabaliſtical-Medicine,</hi> frees us much better from all the
importunate Neceſſities, to which Nature makes the Ignorant ſubject: We
Eat not, but when it pleaſes us; and all the Superfluity of Food Paſſing
away by an inſenſible Tranſpiration, we are never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to be Men.
Here he held<pb n="61" facs="tcp:94889:35"/>his peace, perceiving that we were near our
Servants. So we went to the Village, to take a ſhort Refreſhment; following
the Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the <hi>Philoſophick-Heroes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="discourse">
               <head>Diſcourſe the Third.</head>
               <p>AFter Dinner, we return to to the <hi>Labyrinth.</hi> But I was
ſomewhat Melancholly: &amp; the Pity which I was Affected with, at the
Extravagancy of the <hi>Count,</hi> whom I plainly ſaw incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, hindered
me from taking ſo much Pleaſure at all things, which he had told me, as I
ſhould have done; If I had hoped to have brought him back to his right Wits.
I ſtudied for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing<pb n="62" facs="tcp:94889:36"/>of Antiquity, to puzzle him
with, which he ſhould not be able to Anſwer. For to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to him the
Senſe of the <hi>Church,</hi> was in vain; he having declared, that he only
adhered to the Antient Religion of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the <hi>Philoſophers:</hi>
And to have gone about to Convince a <hi>Cabalist</hi> by Reaſon, would have
been an Enterprize altogether as frivolous. Beſides, I cared not to venture
on a Diſpute with a Man, whoſe Principles I did not yet underſtand.</p>
               <p>It came into my Mind, that what he had told me, concerning the
Falſe <hi>Gods,</hi> in whoſe place he had ſubſtituted the
<hi>Sylphs,</hi> and the other <hi>Elementary</hi> People, might be Refuted by
the <hi>Oracles</hi> of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> which the <hi>Scripture</hi>
mentions alwayes as <hi>Devils,</hi> not as <hi>Sylphs.</hi> But for as much,
as I did not know, if in the Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
of<pb n="63" facs="tcp:94889:36"/>his <hi>Cabal,</hi> the <hi>Count</hi> would not
attribute the Anſwers of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> to ſome Natural Cauſe; I
believed, that it would not be improper, to put him upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining what was
his real O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion herein.</p>
               <p>He gave me a good Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of breaking to him the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
Juſt as we were ready to enter into the <hi>Labyrinth,</hi> turning himſelf
about towards the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: Truly, (ſaid he) it is very Handſom, and theſe
Statues make a Noble Show. The <hi>Cardinal</hi> (reply'd I) who cauſed them
to be ſet here, had an Imagination a little unworthy of his Great
<hi>Genius:</hi> He fancied, that the greateſt part of theſe
<hi>Images</hi> had formerly yielded <hi>Oracles:</hi> And for this very
Conceit, he paid a dear Rate for them. 'Tis the Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of many People,
(ſaid the <hi>Count</hi>) that Ignorance makes them<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94889:37"/>dayly
commit a kind of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> which is very Criminal; ſince they
preſerve with ſo much Care, and put ſo great an Eſteem upon
<hi>Idols,</hi> which they believe the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> has heretofore made
uſe of, to make himſelf Adored. O <hi>God!</hi> Shall it never be known in
the World, that Thou, from the Birth of Times, haſt precipitated thine
Enemies under thy Foot-ſtool? And that Thou keepeſt the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils</hi>
Priſoners under the Earth, in Tormenting Darkneſs? This Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity,
ſomewhat Blame-worthy, of collecting on this manner, theſe pretended Organs
of the <hi>Devils,</hi> might become Innocent, (my Son) if they would ſuffer
themſelves to be perſwaded, that the <hi>Angels</hi> of Darkneſs have
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been permitted to ſpeak in <hi>Oracles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not believe, (interrupted I) that it would be an eaſie
Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<pb n="65" facs="tcp:94889:37"/>to Eſtabliſh this Maxim a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Wits; but
it might be done with thoſe of ſolid Parts. For it has been not long
ſince de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided in a Conference, made ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presſly on this Subject, by the
Wits of the higheſt Rank; That all theſe pretended <hi>Oracles,</hi> were
nothing but the Subtilty of Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricious <hi>Prieſts</hi> amongſt the
<hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils,</hi> or elſe a Politick Stratagem of Princes.</p>
               <p>Were theſe (ſaid the <hi>Count</hi>) <hi>Mahometans,</hi>
ſent on an Ambaſſy to your King, who held this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and thus
decided this Queſtion? No, Sir, (anſwered I.) Of what Religion then, were
theſe Gentlemen, (replyed he) ſince they reckon the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as
nothing; which in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Places, make mention of ſo many different
<hi>Oracles?</hi> And prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally, of the <hi>Pythons;</hi> who made their
Reſidence, and gave<pb n="66" facs="tcp:94889:38"/>out their Anſwers, by thoſe Parts
deſigned for the Multiplication of the Image of <hi>God?</hi> I alledged,
(replyed I) the Examples of thoſe, who diſcours'd from their Bellyes, and
inſtanced to the Company, that <hi>King Saul</hi> had Baniſhed them his
Kingdom; where nevertheleſs he found one who was the Fore-teller of his
Death, whoſe Voyce had the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Power to Raiſe up <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>muel</hi> at
his Requeſt, and to his Ruin. Yet would not theſe Wife-Men decide it
otherwiſe, than that there were never any <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Scriptures did not ſhew it plainly, (ſaid the
<hi>Count</hi>) they might be convinced by all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; wherein it were an
eaſie thing, to bring them a thouſand marvellous Proofs. So many
<hi>Virgins,</hi> big with the Deſtiny of Mortals, who were Deliver'd of 
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:94889:38"/>the good or ill Fortune of thoſe who conſulted them.
Why did you not alledge to them <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, Origen,</hi> and
<hi>Oecumenius?</hi> who make mention of thoſe Divine Men, whom the
<hi>Greeks</hi> called <hi>ENGASTRIMANDRES;</hi> whoſe Prophetick Bellies
delivered out in an Articulate Voyce, ſo Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Oracles.</hi> And if
your Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men loved neither the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> nor the
<hi>Fathers;</hi> thoſe Miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Maids ſhould have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanced, of
whom <hi>Panſanias,</hi> the <hi>Greek</hi> ſpeaks; who changed
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into <hi>Doves,</hi> and in that Form delivered the Famous
<hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of the <hi>Colombae Dodonides.</hi> Or you might have ſaid,
for the Glory of your Nation, That there were long ſince in <hi>Gaule,</hi>
thoſe Illuſtrious Maids, who Metamor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoſed themſelves into all Shapes,
according to the Pleaſure of thoſe who Conſulted them; &amp; who,
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides<pb n="68" facs="tcp:94889:39"/>(the Famous <hi>Oracles</hi> which they gave out)
had a marvellous Command over the Ships at <hi>Sea,</hi> and a Soveraign
healing Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity over the moſt Incurable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
               <p>They would have rejected all theſe Excellent Proofs, as
<hi>Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal,</hi> (ſaid I to him.) Is it (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he) becauſe
Antiquity renders them ſuſpicious? You ſhould but have alledged the
<hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> which are ſtill yielded dayly. In what Part of the World,
(ſaid I?) At <hi>Paris,</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd he.) At <hi>Paris?</hi> (cryed I) Yes,
at <hi>Paris,</hi> (continued he) Are you a Maſter in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and
do you not know that? Do they not dayly Conſult the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quatick
Oracles,</hi> in Glaſſes of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or in Baſins? The <hi>Aerial
O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> in Looking-Glaſſes, and on Maidens Hands? Do they not by
this Means, recover loſt Neck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces<pb n="69" facs="tcp:94889:39"/>or Bracelets, and
ſtolen Watches? Do they not hereby learn News from far Countries? &amp; can
they not ſee thoſe that are Abſent? What is this, Sir, (ſaid I) that
you tell me? I tell you, (reply'd he) what I am ſure, happens every Day, and
of which it will be no difficult Matter, to find a thouſand Ocular
Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. I do not believe that, Sir, (anſwered I:) The Magiſtrates
would make a ſevere Example of any one, who ſhould be found culpable of
ſo puniſhable an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and they would never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuch
<hi>Idolatry</hi>—Alas! How diſcreet you are, (interrupted the
<hi>Count!</hi>) There is not ſo much Harm in all this, as you think: And
Providence will never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe Remains of <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi> to be
wholly Extirpated, that have eſcaped the miſerable Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack, which Truth
has ſuffered.<pb n="70" facs="tcp:94889:40"/>If there be ſtill left among the People
any Footſteps of the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Power of the Divine Names; VVould you
give your Vote for their Effacing? And that they ſhould loſe the Reſpect
and Acknowledgment due to the great Name <hi>AGLA;</hi> which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perates all
theſe Marvels, even then when it is invoked by Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norants, and by Sinners;
and which would work far different Miracles, in the Mouth of a
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balist.</hi> If you would have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced theſe <hi>Gentlemen</hi> of
the Truth of <hi>Oracles,</hi> you needed but have Exalted your Imagination,
and your Faith; and turning your Face towards the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> have cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
with a loud Voyce, <hi>Ag—</hi>Hold, Sir, (interrupted I!) I durſt not
have put in Execution this kind of Argument to ſuch civil Perſons, as
thoſe were with me; for they would have taken<pb n="71" facs="tcp:94889:40"/>me for a
Mad-man: Certainly, they would have had no Faith in all this. And if I had
known, how to have wrought this <hi>Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtick</hi> Operation, of which you
are ſpeaking to me, it would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have come out of my Mouth; becauſe I
have ſtill leſs Faith than they. Well, well, (ſaid the <hi>Count</hi>) if
you have none, we ſhall make it come to you. But further; If you had thought,
that your Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen had not given Credit to what they might have ſeen day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
at <hi>Paris;</hi> you might have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to them a Hiſtory of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
freſh Date. The <hi>Oracle</hi> which <hi>Caelius Rodiginus</hi> ſaid, that
he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had ſeen given forth, about the latter End of the paſt Age,
by that extraordinary Man, who ſpake and fore-told Things to come, by the
ſame <hi>Organ</hi> which the <hi>Euricles,</hi> mentioned by
<hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tark,</hi> did. I would not (anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<pb n="72" facs="tcp:94889:41"/>I) have
cited <hi>Rodiginus;</hi> That Citation had been <hi>Pedantick:</hi>
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, 'tis ten to one, if ſome of them had not told me, that this Man
was certainly Poſſeſſed with a <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That had been ſaid moſt <hi>Fryar-</hi>like, (replyed he.)
Sir, (inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted I) in deſpight of that <hi>Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtick</hi> Averſion,
which I perceive you have for the <hi>Fryars;</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be on their
ſides, in this Point. I believe, that there is not ſo great Harm, in
denying utterly, that ever there were any ſuch things as <hi>Oracles,</hi> as
in ſaying, That it was not the <hi>Devil</hi> who ſpake in them. For in a
word, The <hi>Fathers,</hi> and the <hi>Divines</hi>—For in a word,
(interrupted he) The <hi>Divines,</hi> Do they not agree, that the Wiſe
<hi>Sambetha,</hi> who was the Antienteſt of all the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bils,</hi> was
the Daughter of <hi>Noah?</hi> Well, Sir, (ſaid I) And what of 
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:94889:41"/>that? Did not <hi>Plutarch</hi> (purſued he) ſay, That
the Antienteſt <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bil</hi> was the Firſt who delivered out
<hi>Oracles</hi> at <hi>Delphos?</hi> This Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which <hi>Sambetha</hi>
lodged in her Boſom, was not then a <hi>Devil,</hi> nor her <hi>Apollo</hi> a
Falſe <hi>God;</hi> ſeeing that <hi>Idolatry</hi> did not begin till a long
time after the Diviſion of <hi>Languages:</hi> And it would be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
abſurd, to Attribute to the <hi>Father of Lyes,</hi> thoſe ſacred Books
of the <hi>Sybils,</hi> and all the Proofs of the True <hi>Religion,</hi> which
the <hi>Fathers</hi> have drawn from them. Neither, my Child, (continued he,
ſmiling) is it for you to break the Marriage, which a great <hi>Cardinal</hi>
has made of <hi>David,</hi> and the <hi>Sybil;</hi> nor accuſe this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Perſon, for having put a great <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a miſerable
<hi>Energu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena</hi> in one Parallel. For either <hi>David</hi> ſtrengthens
the Teſtimony of the <hi>Sybil,</hi> or the <hi>Sybil</hi> weakens 
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:94889:42"/>the Authority of <hi>David.</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, Sir,
(interrupted I) fall to your Seriouſneſs again.</p>
               <p>I will, I will (ſaid he) upon Condition, that you will not
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me too much for it. Is the <hi>Devil,</hi> in your Opinion, ever
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt himſelf? And is he any time againſt his own
Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts? Why not? (ſaid I to him) Why not? (ſaid he) Becauſe that
which <hi>Tertullian</hi> hath ſo Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily, and ſo Magnificiently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
the <hi>Reaſon of God,</hi> finds it not convenient. <hi>Satan is never
divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded against himſelf.</hi> It then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that either the
<hi>Devil</hi> never ſpake in <hi>Oracles,</hi> or that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpake
againſt his own Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. And then it follows; That if the
<hi>Oracles</hi> have ſpoken againſt the Intereſts of the <hi>Devil,</hi>
it was not the <hi>Devil</hi> that ſpake in the <hi>Oracles.</hi> But (ſaid
I to him) could not <hi>God</hi> force the <hi>Devil</hi> to bear 
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:94889:42"/>Witneſs to the Truth, and ſpeak againſt himſelf?
But (reply'd he) If <hi>God</hi> did not force him? Nay, in that Caſe
(anſwered I) you have leſs Reaſon than the <hi>Fryers!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us ſee then, (purſued he) Let us proceed Invincibly, and
like good <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> I will not produce the Teſtimonies of
thoſe <hi>Oracles,</hi> of which the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi>
make relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; although I am perſwaded of the Veneration which you have for
theſe Great Men. <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which was their
Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, might have over-ſwayed them; and their Zeal for the Truth,
might have induced them; ſeeing it was cold enough, and naked enough in their
Age, to have borrowed for the cloathing it, ſome Habit, and ſome Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
even from Falſhood it ſelf. They were Men; and by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, 
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:94889:43"/>following the Maxim of the <hi>Poet</hi> of the
<hi>Synagogue,</hi> may have been Unfaithful Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
               <p>I am therefore about to produce a Man, who cannot be
ſuſpected in this Cauſe; a <hi>Pagan:</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother kind of
<hi>Pagan,</hi> than <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretius, Lucian,</hi> or the <hi>Epicureans:</hi> A
<hi>Pagan</hi> poſſeſt with a Real Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, that there are <hi>Gods</hi>
and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils,</hi> without number. He was a Man ſuperſtitious above
mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and a Great <hi>Magician,</hi> or I am much miſtaken in ſaying
it; and by Conſequence, a great Friend of the <hi>Devil:</hi> 'Tis
<hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrius.</hi> Behold ſome of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> which he relates,
word for word.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:94889:43"/> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="oracle">
                           <head>An <hi>ORACLE.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>THere is above the Celeſtial Fire, an Incorruptible
Flame, alwayes ſparkling; the Spring of Life, the Fountain of all Beings, the
Original of all Things! This Flame produceth all Things; and Nothing
periſheth, but what it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes. It makes it Self known by it Self. This
Fire cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in any Place: 'Tis without Body, and without Matter.
It en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſes the Heavens: And there goes out from it a little Spark,
which makes all the Fire of the <hi>Sun,</hi> of the <hi>Moon,</hi> and of the
<hi>Stars.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold! What I know of <hi>God!</hi> Strive not to Know more
of him; for that is beyond thy Capacity, how Wiſe ſo-ever thou art. As to
the reſt; Know, that unjuſt and wicked Man, cannot hide himſelf from the
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence<pb n="78" facs="tcp:94889:44"/>of <hi>God!</hi> No Subtilty, nor Excuſe, can
diſguiſe any thing from his peirceing Eyes. All is full of <hi>God,</hi>
and <hi>God</hi> is in All!</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee here, (my Son) that this <hi>Oracle,</hi> ſavours
not very much of the <hi>Devil.</hi> At leaſt, (anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I) the
<hi>Devil</hi> in this, is very wide from the Character which is given of him.
Here is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (anſwered he) which is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther better.</p>
               <p> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="oracle">
                           <head>An <hi>ORACLE.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>THere is in <hi>God</hi> an Immenſe Profoundity of
Flame! Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, the Heart ſhould not fear to touch this Adorable
Fire, or to be touched by it: It will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be conſumed by this ſo ſweet
Fire; whoſe Mild and Tranquil<pb n="79" facs="tcp:94889:44"/>Heat, makes the Binding, the
Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and the Duration of the World. Nothing ſubſiſts but by this
Fire, which is <hi>God</hi> Himſelf. No Perſon begot Him: He is without
Mother: He knows all Things, and can be taught Nothing. He is Infallible in his
Deſignes, and his Name is unſpeakable. Behold now, what <hi>God</hi> is! As
for Us, who are his Meſſengers; WE ARE BUT A LITTLE PART OF GOD.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Well, Sir! What ſay you now to this? I would ſay to both
theſe, (reply'd I) That <hi>God</hi> can force the <hi>Father of Lyes,</hi>
to bear Witneſs to the Truth. Pray then obſerve another, (continued the
<hi>Count</hi>) which will clear <hi>you</hi> of this Scruple.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:94889:45"/> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="oracle">
                           <head>An <hi>ORACLE.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>ALas, O ye <hi>TRIPODES!</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and make the
Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Oration of your <hi>Apollo:</hi> HE IS MORTAL! HE IS GOING TO DYE! HE
IS EXTINCT! Becauſe the Light of the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Flame makes him
extinguiſh.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee plainly, (my Son) that he, whatſoever he be, that
ſpeaks in theſe <hi>Oracles,</hi> and who ſo well explains to the
<hi>Pagans,</hi> the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, the Unity, the Immenſity, and the Eternity
of <hi>God;</hi> He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that he is Mortal, and that he is but a Spark of
<hi>God.</hi> It is not therefore the <hi>Devil</hi> who Speaks, ſince he is
Immortal; and that <hi>God</hi> would not force him to ſay, that he was not
ſo. It is concluded, that <hi>Satan</hi> is never di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided<pb n="81" facs="tcp:94889:45"/>againſt himſelf. For, Would it be the way to make him Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to
ſay, that there is but one <hi>God?</hi> He ſayes, That he is Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.
Since when, has the <hi>Devil</hi> been ſo Humble, as to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from his
Natural Qualities? You may ſee then, (my Son) that if the Being of Him who is
called by way of Excellence, the <hi>God of Knowledge,</hi> ſubſiſts, it
can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the <hi>Devil,</hi> who ſpake in the <hi>Oracles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if it be not the <hi>Devil,</hi> (ſaid I to him) either
Lying out of the Wantonneſs of his Heart, or tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Truth by Conſtraint,
when he ſpeaks of <hi>God;</hi> To what then will your <hi>Cabal</hi>
attribute all theſe <hi>Oracles,</hi> which you maintain, have been really
given forth? Is it to an Exhalation of the Earth, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,
Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? No ſuch thing, my Child,
(ſaid the <hi>Count</hi>) Thanks to the<pb n="82" facs="tcp:94889:46"/>Sacred
<hi>Cabal,</hi> I have not my Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination clouded to ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. How?
(replyed I) Do you Eſteem this Opinion ſo Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick? The Favourers of it,
are Perſons of clear Senſe: They are not, my Child, I can aſſure you,
of this Judgment, (continued he) It is impoſſible, to attribute to this
Exhaltion, all what has paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in theſe <hi>Oracles.</hi> As for
Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; That Man (ſpoken of by <hi>Tacitus</hi>) who appeared in a Dream to
the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Hercules's</hi> Temple in <hi>Armenia,</hi> and
commanded them to get them Horſes ready for Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Thus far might it have
been an Exhalation: But when theſe <hi>Courſers</hi> returned at Night
quite tyred, and their Quivers emptied of all their Arrows; and that the next
Morning, there were found as many Beaſts kil'd in the Forreſt, as they had
put Arrows into their Quivers: You muſt<pb n="83" facs="tcp:94889:46"/>confeſs, that it
could not be an Exhaltion, that could work this Effect. It could leſs be the
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> for that would be to have a Notion not at all Reaſonable,
nor <hi>Cabaliſtick,</hi> of the Miſery of the Enemy of <hi>God,</hi> to
think, that he were permitted to divert him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with Courſing of
<hi>Hares,</hi> and <hi>Wild-Beaſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To what then (ſaid I to him) does the Sacred <hi>Cabal</hi>
attribute all this? Hold (anſwered he) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I diſcover this Myſtery to
you, I muſt cure your Spirits of this Fancy, with which they may be
prepoſſeſſed, concerning this pretended Exhalation; for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought,
that you cited with an Emphaſis, <hi>Ariſtotle, Plutarch,</hi> and
<hi>Cicero:</hi> You might likewiſe have cited <hi>Jamblicus,</hi> who, as
great a Wit as he was, was ſome time in this Error; which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, he
ſoon quitted, after he<pb n="84" facs="tcp:94889:47"/>had better examined the Matter in
the Book of <hi>Myſteries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Petrus Aponius, Pomponacius, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinius, Sirenius,</hi> and
<hi>Lucilius Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus,</hi> are infinitly pleaſed to have found this Defect
in any of the <hi>Antients.</hi> All theſe pretended great Wits, who when
they ſpeak of Divine things, rather ſay what they deſire, than what they
know; they will not allow any thing Supernatural to be in <hi>Oracles,</hi> for
fear of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging ſomething above man, They are ſo afraid, to have a
Ladder made them to Climb up to God; that they dare not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge by
degrees, theſe Spiritual Creatures: they rather chooſe to build one, to
Deſcend by it into nothing. Inſtead of raiſeing themſelves up towards
Heaven, they Creep down into the Earth: and inſtead of mans ſearching among
the Superiour<pb n="85" facs="tcp:94889:47"/>Beings, for the Cauſe of theſe
Tranſports, which carry him above himſelf, and make him in a manner a
Divinity, they weakly Attribute to impower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Exhalation. This force of
penetrating into what is to come, of diſcovering things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd, and
Advancing himſelf up, even to the higheſt Secrets of the Divine
Eſſence.</p>
               <p>Such is the miſery of Man, when the Spirit of Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
and Humor of thinking con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to others, does poſſeſs him! Far off from
attaining his Ends, he runs himſelf into a miſt, and loſes himſelf.
Theſe <hi>Libertines</hi> will not ſubject men to Subſtances, leſs
material than himſelf, and yet, ſubject him to an Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And without
conſidering that there is no parallel between this <hi>Chymerick Smoke,</hi>
and the Soul of man, between this Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour<pb n="86" facs="tcp:94889:48"/>and future things,
between this frivolous Cauſe, and theſe miraculous Effects. It ſuffices
them to be ſingular, to believe, that they are reaſonable; 'Tis enough for
them to deny Spirits, and alſo to uphold the power of them.</p>
               <p>Then does ſingularity ſo much diſpleaſe you, Sir?
(interrupted I) Ah my Son! (ſaid he to me) 'Tis the Peſt of good ſenſe,
and the ſtumbling-block of the greateſt Wits. <hi>Aristotle</hi> as great a
<hi>Logician</hi> as he was, knew not how to avoid this infection, or
phantaſy of ſingularity, much leſs thoſe whom it works up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as
violently as him; He could not avoid (I ſay) puzling himſelf, nor knew he
how to get clear again. He ſays in his Book of <hi>The Generation of
Animalls,</hi> and in his <hi>Morals,</hi> That the Wit and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of
a man comes to<pb n="87" facs="tcp:94889:48"/>him from without, and that it cannot come to
us from our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and by the ſpirituality of the operations of our Soul,
he concludes, that it is of another nature, than this material com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition
which it Animates, and whereof the groſeneſs does but cloud the
ſpeculations, not at all contributing to their Production. Blind
<hi>Ariſtotle!</hi> ſince that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your ſenſe, our materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
Compoſition cannot be the fource of our ſpiritual Thoughts, what do you
mean, that a weak Exhalation, can be the cauſe of moſt ſublime Thoughts,
and of the Raptures wherewith the <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> were ſeized, when they
thus gave out their <hi>Oracles.</hi> You may eaſily ſee (my Child) that
this great Wit Came ſhort; and that his Singularity was the Cauſe of it.
You reaſon very juſtly, Sir, (ſaid I to him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<pb n="88" facs="tcp:94889:49"/>infinitly pleaſed to hear at laſt, that he ſpake very good
Senſe; and hoping Folly was not an incureable evil) I would to <hi>God</hi>
that—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch,</hi> though otherwiſe ſolid, (continued he,
interrupting me) in his Dialogue, is ſorry, that the <hi>Oracles</hi> were
Ceas'd. He Objects convincing reaſons, which he leaves unreſolved. Why does
he not anſwer, to what is ſaid? That if it be an Exhalation, which is
cauſe of this Tranſport, all thoſe who approach the <hi>Prophetick
Tripos,</hi> would be ſeized with an <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſme;</hi> and not one
Maid only, and ſhe alſo muſt be a Virgin. But how could this Voice make
an Articulate Sound, through the Belly? Moreover, this. Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a
Natural Cauſe, and of neceſſity, muſt work its Effect regularly, and
always; Why<pb n="89" facs="tcp:94889:49"/>then is not this Maid inſpir'd, but then when
ſhe is conſulted? And what is more to the Purpoſe? Why has the Earth
ceaſed to vent thoſe Divine Vapors? Is it leſs Earth, than it was? Has it
received other Influences? Hath it other <hi>Rivers,</hi> and other
<hi>Seas?</hi> Who elſe has thus open'd its Pores, or chang'd its
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>I admire <hi>Pomponacius, Lucilius,</hi> and other
<hi>Libertines,</hi> for having taken this Idaea of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and left
the manner whereby he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains it. He ſpake more Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, than
<hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> as being a Man of good Reaſon:
<hi>But</hi> not knowing what to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude of all theſe <hi>Oracles,</hi>
after a tedious irreſolution, he gives his Opinion, that this Exhalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
which he believed came out of the Earth, was a moſt <hi>Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi>
So he Attributed to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:94889:50"/>theſe Motions,
and theſe extraordinary Lights of the <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteſſes</hi> of
<hi>Apollo. This Divining Vapour</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is a moſt Divine
Breath, and a most Holy Spirit. Pomponacius, Lucilius,</hi> and the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern
<hi>Athiſts,</hi> do not conclude it in this phraſe of Speech, which
ſuppoſes a <hi>Divinity.</hi> Theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations (ſay they) were of the
nature of thoſe Vapours which infeſted the <hi>Hypocondriacks,</hi> who
ſpake Languages which they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not. But <hi>Fernelius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futes
theſe Impious <hi>Wretches</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, by proving, that the Bile, which
is a ſmarting humour, cannot cauſe this diverſity of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, which is
one of the moſt marvellous Effects of conſideration, and an Artificial
Expreſſion of our thoughts. Nevertheleſs he has decided the point but
imperfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; when he has ſubſcribed to <hi>Pſellius,</hi> and all
thoſe who have<pb n="91" facs="tcp:94889:50"/>not penetrated deep enough in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our holy
Phyloſophy. Not knowing where to find the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of theſe ſo
unapprehenſible Effects. He has imitated the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and <hi>Nunns,</hi> and
attributed them to the Devil. To what then muſt they be attributed, (ſaid I
to him) for I have been long expecting this Cabaliſtique ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> alſo has very well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved (ſaid he to
me) and he had done well, if he had ſtopped there. This irregular manner of
explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſelf by an indecent Organ, not being grave enough, nor
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting the Majeſty of the Gods (ſaid this <hi>Pagan</hi>) and that
which the <hi>Oracles</hi> did ſay, ſurpaſſing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the power of the
Soul of Man; Thoſe have rendred a great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Phyloſophy, who have
eſtabliſhed mortal creatures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Gods and Men, to 
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:94889:51"/>whom might be imputed all that which ſurpaſſes humane
weakneſs, and which approaches not to the Divine Granduer.</p>
               <p>This is the opinion of all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Phyloſophy. The
<hi>Platoniſts</hi> and <hi>Pythagorians</hi> took it from the
<hi>Egyptians,</hi> and they from <hi>Joſeph</hi> the <hi>Patriarch,</hi> and
from the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> who dwelt in <hi>Eygypt</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their
paſſage through the <hi>Red-Sea.</hi> The <hi>Hebrews</hi> called theſe
ſubſtances which are between an Angel and a Man, <hi>Sadaim;</hi> and the
<hi>Greeks</hi> tranſpoſing the Silla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and adding two Letters, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
them <hi>Diamonas.</hi> Theſe <hi>Demons</hi> according to the antient
Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, were an Aerial People, bearing rule over the Elements, Mortal,
ingendring and multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; unknown in this Age, by by thoſe who make but
little ſearch after Truth in her ancient Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that is to ſay, in the
<hi>Cabal,</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:94889:51"/>and in the <hi>Theology</hi> of the
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> who had <hi>found out</hi> amongſt them the particular art
of enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining this Aerial Nation, and of converſing with all the
inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Air.—</p>
               <p>Why, Look ye here, Sir, you are come again to your
<hi>Sylphes</hi> (interrupted I) yes my Son (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he) The
<hi>Teraphim</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> was nothing but the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony which was
to be obſerved for this commerce; and the <hi>Jew Micha</hi> who complained
in the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> that they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away his Gods, crys not
but for the loſs of a little Statue in which the <hi>Sylphes</hi> entertained
him. The Gods which <hi>Rachel</hi> ſtole from her Father was alſo a
<hi>Teraphim. Micha</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> were neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of Idolatry,
and <hi>Jacob</hi> would never have been perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to live forty Years with
an Idolater, nor have eſpouſed his<pb n="94" facs="tcp:94889:52"/>Daughter, it was but
a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the <hi>Sylphes;</hi> and we know by tradition, that the
<hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagoge</hi> was permitted this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and the Idolatry of
<hi>Davids</hi> Wife was but a <hi>Teraphim,</hi> by fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of which ſhe entertained the Elementary People. For
you may well imagine that the Prophet after Gods own Heart, would not have
ſuffered Idolatry in his Houſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe Elementary Nations, ſo long as God deferred the
Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, by puniſhment of the firſt Sin, took pleaſure to
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to men through the <hi>Oracles,</hi> what they knew of God; to teach
them to live morally, to give them moſt ſage and proffitable councels,
ſuch as thoſe which we find in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> and in all the
Hiſtorians. But ſince that God took pitty of the World, and would himſelf
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come its Doctor, theſe little Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters<pb n="95" facs="tcp:94889:52"/>retired
themſelves, and hence proceeded the Silence of the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reſult then of all your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, Sir (ſaid I) is,
that there have certainly been <hi>Oracles,</hi> and that it was the
<hi>Sylphs</hi> who delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, and who ſtill do yeild them dayly in
<hi>Drinking</hi> Glaſſes, or <hi>Looking</hi> Glaſſes. The
<hi>Sylphs,</hi> or the <hi>Salamanders,</hi> the <hi>Gnomes</hi> or the
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndians</hi> (replyed the Count) If it be ſo, (ſaid I) All the
<hi>Elementary</hi> People are very diſhoneſt. Why ſo (ſaid he?) Why,
was there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſuch knavery ſeen (purſued I) as all thoſe anſwers in
a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſence, which they always gave out? Always, (replyed he?) no no, not
always. That <hi>Sylphide</hi> who appeared to <hi>Q. Curtius Rufus</hi> the
<hi>Roman</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> at the Town of <hi>Adrimetum,</hi> who
fore-told to him that he ſhould one day attain to the dignity of
<hi>Proconſul:</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:94889:53"/>Did ſhe ſpeak obſcurely? And
does not <hi>Tacitus,</hi> and <hi>Plinius Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundus</hi> relate, how thoſe
things came to paſs, which ſhe fore-told? That in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cription, and the Famous <hi>Pistures,</hi> mentioned in
the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>Spain,</hi> which were ſeen by the unfortunate King
<hi>Don Rogri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> the Second, that his curioſity in opening the Enchanted
Cave, and his Incontinence, in deflouring the 
<note n="*" place="margin">Elvira.</note>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Count
<hi>Don Julian,</hi> ſhould be puniſhed by men Habited and Armed after the
ſame manner as thoſe Pict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ures were, and that theſe ſwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy men, being
the Arabians or Moores ſhould Conquer <hi>Spain,</hi> and Raign a long time
therein. Could all this be more clear, and did not the fulfilling thereof that
ſame year, Juſtify it ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently? Came not the <hi>Moores</hi> to
Dethrone this Effeminate King?<pb n="97" facs="tcp:94889:53"/>as you know the Hiſtory:
And you may plainly ſee, that the Devil, who ſince the Reign, of the
<hi>Meſſias,</hi> does not diſpoſe of Empires, could not be the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
of this <hi>Oracle,</hi> and that it was certainly ſome great
<hi>Cabaliſt,</hi> who had learnt it of ſome of the moſt knowing
<hi>Salamanders.</hi> For as the <hi>Salamanders</hi> do very much love
Chaſtity, they willingly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn us of the Miſchiefs which muſt happen
in the World by the Defect of this Virtue.</p>
               <p>But, with your Pardon Sir, (ſaid I to him) do you eſteem
that <hi>Heteroclite Organ,</hi> becoming the <hi>Cabaliſtick-</hi>Modeſty,
out of which they uſe to Preach their Morality? Alaſs! (ſaid the
<hi>Count,</hi> ſmiling) now have you again your Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation clouded; and
you ſee not the <hi>Phyſical</hi> Reaſon for this, that the enflamed
<hi>Salamander</hi> is naturally delighted to be in<pb n="98" facs="tcp:94889:54"/>the
moſt Fiery Places, and is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted by the—I underſtand, I
underſtand you, (interrupted I) you need not give your ſelf the trouble to
explain it further.</p>
               <p>And as to the Obſcurity of ſome <hi>Oracles,</hi> (proceeded
he, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly) which you call an Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture; Is not Darkneſs the
ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Habit of Truth? Is not <hi>God</hi> pleaſed to conceal himſelf in
their dark Shaddows? And the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual <hi>Oracle,</hi> which he has left to
his Children, the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> were not they clouded with an
Adorable Obſcurity, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds and diſtracts the Proud, as much as
his Light guides the Humble?</p>
               <p>If you have but this Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, my Son, I would adviſe you,
not to defer your entring into a Commerce with the <hi>Elementary People.</hi>
You ſhall find them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Honeſt, full of Underſtanding, 
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:94889:54"/>Lovers to do good, and fearing <hi>God.</hi> And I ſhould
councel you, to begin with a <hi>Salamander:</hi> For you have <hi>Mars</hi> in
the Height of <hi>Heaven,</hi> in your Figure; which is an infallible Signe,
that there is a great deal of Fire in your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And as for your Marriage,
I am of opinion, that if you take a <hi>Sylphide,</hi> you would be Happyer
with her, than any of the others; as having <hi>Jupiter</hi> at the Angle of
your Aſcendant, which <hi>VEN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> looks upon from a <hi>Sextile.</hi>
Now <hi>Jupiter</hi> Rules over the Air, and the People of the Air.
Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, you muſt conſult your Heart above all; for as you will one
day ſee, 'tis by the Interior Stars, which the <hi>Sage</hi> is Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by:
And the Stars of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior Heaven, ſerve but to make him know more
certainly, the Aſpects of the Stars of the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Heaven, which is in
every<pb n="100" facs="tcp:94889:55"/>Creature. So therefore, 'tis you now, that muſt
tell me what your Inclination is; to the end, that we may proceed to your
Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance with theſe <hi>Elementary Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> which you ſhall like
beſt. Sir, (anſwered I) This Affair, in my Opinion, requires a little
Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. I like you for this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, (ſaid he to me, laying his
Hand upon my Shoulder.) Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult this Affair ſeriouſly with him, who for
Excellency we call, <hi>The Angel of the great Council.</hi> Go kneel down to
Prayer, and I ſhall come to you to Morrow at Two a Clock in the
Afternoon.</p>
               <p>We came back for <hi>Paris;</hi> and I, as we were upon our way,
put him again upon the Diſcourſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and
<hi>Libertines:</hi> But I never heard one argue, nor ſpeak ſo well, ſuch
high, and ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Things, for the Exiſtence of <hi>God,</hi> and
againſt the Blindneſs of<pb n="101" facs="tcp:94889:55"/>thoſe, who ſpend their
Lives, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving up themſelves intirely to a ſerious and continual
Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of him; from whom we have, and who likewiſe preſerves our Being.
I was amazed at the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of this Man; and was not able to comprehend how
it could be, that he ſhould at the ſame time, be ſo Strong, and ſo
Weak; ſo Admirable, and ſo Ridiculous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="discourse">
               <head>Diſcourſe the Fourth.</head>
               <p>I Expected at my Houſe, my Lord the <hi>Count</hi> of
<hi>Gabalis,</hi> as we had agreed upon it, at our Parting. He came at the
prefixed Hour: And accoſting me with a ſmiling Look; Well 
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:94889:56"/>now, my Son, (ſaid he to me) which ſort of the
Inviſible Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, has <hi>God</hi> given you the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Appetite to?
And, What Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance do you like beſt; that of the <hi>Salamanders,</hi> of
the <hi>Gnomes,</hi> of the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> or of the <hi>Nymphs?</hi> Sir,
(anſwer'd I) I have not yet fully reſolved upon this Marriage. Why? where
ſticks it now? (demanded he.) To deal freely and plainly with you, Sir,
(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed I to him) I cannot yet cure my Imagination; that ſtill repreſents
to me, all theſe Hoſts of the <hi>Elements,</hi> as <hi>Legions</hi> of
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</hi> O Lord! (cryed he) thou <hi>God</hi> of Light, I beſeech
thee, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate the Clouds, which Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and perverſe Education,
have thruſt into the Spirit of this idcredulous Man; whom Thou haſt made me
know, is one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for ſo great Things! And you, my Son, Do not ſhut
up<pb n="103" facs="tcp:94889:56"/>the Paſſage to this Truth, which<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>might enter into
you. Be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible: But now, I diſpence with your being ſo; for I might ſo
be Injurious to the Truth, to prepare its wayes: She knows how to force open
Gates of Iron, and can enter where ſhe liſts, in deſpight of all the
Reſiſtance of Falſhood. What can induce you to oppoſe it? Is it
becauſe you think, that <hi>God</hi> could not create theſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
in the Elements, ſuch as I have been painting out to you?</p>
               <p>I am not well ſatisfyed, (ſaid I to him) whether or no there
be a Poſſibility in the Thing it ſelf; if one Element can furniſh
Blood, Fleſh, and Bones; if there can be a Temperament without Mixture, and
Actions without Contrariety. But ſuppoſe <hi>God</hi> could make it, What
ſolid Proof is there, that he did make it?</p>
               <p>Shall I convince you now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently<pb n="104" facs="tcp:94889:57"/>(replyed he) without any more ado? I will cauſe to come hither the
<hi>Sylphs</hi> of <hi>Cardan:</hi> You may underſtand from their own Mouths,
what they are, and what I have been teaching you of them. By no means, I
beſeech you, (cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I out, affrightedly) Forbear, I conjure you, this kind
of Proof, till ſuch time as I ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that theſe ſame
People are not Enemies to <hi>God:</hi> For as to that, I ſhould rather
chooſe to Dye, than give this trouble to my Conſcience of—</p>
               <p>Behold! Behold the ignorant and falſe Piety of theſe unhappy
Times! (interrupted the <hi>Count,</hi> in a Cholerick Tone.) Why then do they
not blot out of the Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Saints, the greateſt of all the
<hi>Anachorites?</hi> And, Why do they not burn his Statues? 'Tis a great
wonder, that they inſult not over his venerable Aſhes!<pb n="105" facs="tcp:94889:57"/>And that they ſcatter them not in the VVind, as they have done to
thoſe unhappy Wretches, who have been Accuſed for having had Commerce with
the <hi>Devils.</hi> Are we adviſed to Exorcize the <hi>Sylphs?</hi> And have
they not been treated as Men? What have you to ſay to that <hi>Maſter
Scrupulous,</hi> you, and all your miſerable Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors? The <hi>Sylphe,</hi>
who diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of his own Nature to this <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch,</hi> Was it, in
your opinion, an Imp of the <hi>Devil?</hi> Was it with a Fiend, that this
incomparable Man argued about the <hi>Goſpel?</hi> And will you accuſe him,
for having profaned the adorable My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, in diſcourſing them with a
Phantaſme, an Enemy of <hi>God? Athanaſius,</hi> and <hi>Hierom,</hi> are
then very unworthy of the great Name, which they have amongſt your
Wiſe-Men, for having writ with ſo much Eloquence, the <hi>Elogy</hi> of 
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:94889:58"/>a Man who treated the <hi>Devils</hi> ſo Humanly. If
they took this <hi>Sylphe</hi> for a <hi>Devil,</hi> the Adventure ſhould
have been concealed, or the Preaching of a Spirit retrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and this ſo
pathetick Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe, which the <hi>Anachoret,</hi> (more zealous, &amp;
more credulous than you) made at the City of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> And if they
have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it for a Creature, having a ſhare, as it aſſured him, in the
Redemption as well as we. And if this Apparition, according to their opinion,
be an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Favor which <hi>God</hi> did the Saint, whoſe Life they
writ; Are you in your Wits, that would appear to be wiſer than
<hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Hierom;</hi> and more Holy than the Divine Saint
<hi>Anthony?</hi> What would you have ſaid to this Man, had you been of the
Number of the Ten Thouſand ſolitary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to whom he related the 
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:94889:58"/>Converſation, which he had new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoy'd with the
<hi>Sylphe?</hi> Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and more enlightned, than all theſe Terreſtrial
Angels. You had, without doubt, remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Holy <hi>Abbot,</hi>
that his Adventure was but a meer Illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And you had diſwaded his
Diſciple <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> from publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all the World, a
Hiſtory ſo little conformable to Religion, to <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi> and to
Common Senſe. Is it not true?</p>
               <p>'Tis true (ſaid I to him) that I ſhould have been of opinion
ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have ſaid nothing at all, elſe to have ſaid nothing at all,
elſe to have ſaid more. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Hierom</hi>
(purſued he) cared not for ſaying more, for they knew no better than that;
and if they had known all, which they could not do, unleſs they had been of
us, they would not have raſhly devulged the ſecrets of the
<hi>Sages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:94889:59"/>But why (ſaid I) did not this
<hi>Sylphe</hi> propoſe to Saint <hi>Anthony,</hi> what you propoſed to me
to day? what's that (ſaid the Count, Smil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) Marriage? alas! Had this been
to any purpoſe? 'Tis true (replyed I) that in all likelyhood, the Good Man
would not have accepted the proffer. No cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly (ſaid the Count) for it
would have been to tempt God, to have Marryed at that Age, and to have
deſired Children of him. How? (demanded I) then do they Marry with theſe
<hi>Sylphes,</hi> to have Children by them? Why, (ſaid he) who was ever
permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be Marryed for any other end? I did not think, (anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red I)
that this had been intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Propagation. I had ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that the
End, and Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all this, had been but to Immortalize the
<hi>Sylphides.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ha! (purſued lie) you are<pb n="109" facs="tcp:94889:59"/>Waggiſh. The
Charity of the Phyloſophers propoſes for its end, the immortality of the
<hi>Sylphides:</hi> but Nature makes them deſire to ſee them Fruitful. You
ſhall ſee when you pleaſe, in the Air the Phyloſophique Families. It
were a happy World, were there none but theſe Families, and if there were
none of the Children of Sin. What do you mean by the Children of Sin? Sir
(inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted I.)</p>
               <p>They are (my Son, continued he) They are all thoſe Children
who are born after the ordinary way; Children conceived by the Will of the
Fleſh, not by the Will of God; Children of Wrath, and of the Curſe; In a
word, Children of Man and Woman. You have a mind to interrupt me. I perceive,
what you would ſay to me. 'Tis true, (my Child) You muſt know that it was
ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<pb n="110" facs="tcp:94889:60"/>the Will of God, that Man and Woman ſhould have
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as they have. The deſign of the moſt prudent Artiſt was far
more noble, he intended to have peopled the World, after a different manner
than it is. If <hi>the</hi> miſerable <hi>Adam,</hi> had not foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly
diſobeyed the order which he had from God, not to touch <hi>Eve;</hi> and
that he had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the other Fruits of the Garden of pleaſure,
with all the Beautys of the <hi>Nymphs</hi> and <hi>Sylphides:</hi> The World
had not ſuffered the ſhame of ſeeing it ſelf peopled with Men ſo
imperfect, that they may paſs for Monſters, where the Children of
Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers are preſent.</p>
               <p>How Sir (ſaid I to him) you think, ſo far as I perceive,
that the Sin of <hi>Adam</hi> was ſomething elſe than eating of the Apple?
Why, my Son (replied the Count)<pb n="111" facs="tcp:94889:60"/>are you of the Number of
thoſe, who have the ſimplicity, to take the Hiſtory of the Apple, in the
litteral ſence? Alas! you muſt know, that the Holy Tongue uſes innocent
Metaphors, to remove from us, the unſeemly Ideas of an action, which has been
cauſe of all the miſeries of mankind. For ſo, when <hi>Saloman</hi>
ſaid, <hi>I will get upon the</hi> Palm, <hi>and I will gather the Fruits
thereof;</hi> He had another Appetite than eating Dates. This Tongue which the
Angels conſecrate, and whereof they make uſe, to ſing their Hymns to the
Living God; has not a term to expreſs that, which it names figuratively an
Apple or Date. But the <hi>Sage</hi> unriddles theſe chaſt figures, when he
ſees that the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat and Mouth of <hi>Eve</hi> eſcape unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and
that ſhe brings forth with pain, he knew that it was not the Pallat that had
been cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal;<pb n="112" facs="tcp:94889:61"/>and diſcovering what the firſt Sin was,
by the care which the firſt Sinners took to cover with leaves certain parts
of their Bodies; He concluded that God would not have had men multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply by this
beaſtly way. O <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam!</hi> thou ſhouldeſt not have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got men, but
ſuch as ſhould have been like thy ſelf, or elſe. <hi>Heroes</hi> or
<hi>Gyants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alas! what expedient (interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted I) can there be for
reparation of one or other of theſe marvellous generations. Obey God (replyed
he) Touch none but the <hi>Nymphs,</hi> the <hi>Gnomes,</hi> the
<hi>Sylphides,</hi> or the <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders.</hi> So ſhould we ſee
<hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> born, and the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> fill'd with marvellous
People, repleat with ſtrength and wiſdome. God would have us conjecture the
difference, which there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that Innocent, and this Culpable World
which we ſee;<pb n="113" facs="tcp:94889:61"/>By permitting us from time to time, to
ſee Children Born, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that manner which he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. Then has there
Sir (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted I) been now and then ſeen of theſe Children of the
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements? If ſo, a Licenciate of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> who quoted to me the
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, St. <hi>Augustin,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> of
<hi>Nazianzen,</hi> is miſtaken, believing that there could not be any fruit
produced, of theſe amours with Spirits for our Wives, or by the commerce that
men might have with certain Devils, which he called <hi>Hyphialtes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> has diſcourſed it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (replyed the
Count) and the ſolid <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> has wiſely reſolved it,
that the commerces would not only be Fruitful, but that the Children which are
Born from them, are of a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and more heroick nature. You ſhall
read at large, when you<pb n="114" facs="tcp:94889:62"/>pleaſe, the great Atchievements
of the puiſſant and famous men, which <hi>Moſes</hi> writes of: born
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner; we have the Hiſtories by us. In the Book of the Wars of
the Lord, mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the three and twentyeth Chapter of <hi>Numbers.</hi> In
the mean time Judge what the World would be, if all its Inhabitants were, for
example, like <hi>Zoroaſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zoroaſter,</hi> (ſaid I) who by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port was the Author
of <hi>Necroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy?</hi> The very ſame (ſaid the <hi>Count</hi>) of whom
the Ignorants write this Calumny. He had the Honour to be ſon of the
Salamander <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> and <hi>Vesta,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Noah:</hi>
He lived twelve Hundred Years, the moſt Sage Monarch of the World; and then
was carried up by his Father <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> into the Region of the
<hi>Salamanders.</hi> I do not doubt (ſaid I to him) but that
<hi>Zoroaster</hi>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:94889:62"/>is with the <hi>Salamander
Oromaſis</hi> in the Region of Fire: But I would not do to <hi>Noah</hi> that
injury, which you do him.</p>
               <p>The injury, is not ſo great as you may believe; (anſwered
the <hi>Count</hi>) all theſe Patriarches e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed it a great honour to be
the ſuppoſed Fathers which the Children of God had by their Wives: But
ſtill this is out of your Element. Let us come to <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> he was
beloved by <hi>Veſta,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Noah.</hi> This <hi>Veſta</hi>
being Dead, was the Tutelar Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the ſacred Fire,
which ſhe ordained that the Virgins ſhould preſerve with ſo much Care,
was, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the <hi>Salamander</hi> her Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant. Beſides
<hi>Zoroaſter,</hi> there was born from their Loines, a Daughter of rare
Beauty, and of an excellent Wiſdom; It was the divine <hi>Egeria,</hi> from
whom<pb n="116" facs="tcp:94889:63"/>
                  <hi>Numa Pauphilius</hi> received all his Laws. She
obliged <hi>Numa,</hi> who loved her, to erect a Temple to her mother
<hi>Veſta,</hi> where that ſacred Fire was kept in honour of her Father
<hi>Oromaſis.</hi> Behold the verity of the Fable, which the Roman Poets and
Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have conceived of the Nymph <hi>Egeria. Gulielmus
Poſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> one of the leaſt ignorant of all thoſe who have
ſtudied the Cabal in his ordinary Books, has obſerv'd that
<hi>Veſta,</hi> was the Daughter of <hi>Noah:</hi> But he was ignorant that
<hi>Egeria</hi> was Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that <hi>Veſta,</hi> and having read the
ſecret Books of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Cabal, of which the Prince of <hi>Miranda</hi>
bought a Copy at ſo dear a rate. He has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded things, believing only
that <hi>Egeria</hi> was the good Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of <hi>Noah's</hi> Wife: But we learn
in theſe Books, that <hi>Egeria</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:94889:63"/>was Conceived upon
the Waters, at that time when as <hi>Noah</hi> was toſſed to and fro, on
thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging Waves, which drown'd the Univerſe: The women then were
reduced to that ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who were ſav'd in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſque Ark,
which this ſecond Father of the world had built. This great man lamented to
ſee the dreadful puniſhment, with which the Lord chaſtiſed the Crime,
cauſed by the Love, which <hi>Adam</hi> had had for his <hi>Eve.</hi> Seeing
that <hi>Adam</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed his Poſterity, by prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<hi>Eve</hi> before the Daughters of the <hi>Elements;</hi> and by taking her
from the <hi>Salamanders</hi> or <hi>Sylphs,</hi> which knew how to make
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves beloved by her. <hi>Noah,</hi> I ſay, became Wiſe by the
ſad example of <hi>Adam,</hi> conſented, that <hi>Vesta</hi> his Wife,
ſhould be given to the Salamander <hi>Oroma-Oromaſis,</hi> 
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:94889:64"/>Prince of the Igne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Subſtances; and perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his
three Children alſo, to give their three Wives, to the Princes of the three
other Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Univerſe in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time was repeopled with He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick
Men, ſo Wiſe, ſo Beautiful, and ſo Admirable, that their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity
admiring their Vertue, have adored them as Deities. One of the Children of
<hi>Noah</hi> Rebelled againſt the Counſel of his Father, not being able to
reſiſt the attractions of his Wife, no more than <hi>Adam</hi> could the
Charms of his <hi>Eve:</hi> But as the ſin of <hi>Adam</hi> had left a
Tincture upon the Souls of all his <hi>Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants;</hi> ſo this want of
compla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, which <hi>Cham</hi> had for the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> marked all his
Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity Black. Hence comes (ſay our <hi>Cabaliſtes</hi>) that Horrible
Blackneſs of the <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> and<pb n="119" facs="tcp:94889:64"/>all thoſe
hideous People, who are commanded to dwell under the <hi>Torrid Zone,</hi> as a
puniſhent for the profane Appetite of their Father.</p>
               <p>Theſe are very particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations Sir (ſaid I, admiring
the Extravagancy of this man) and it ſeemes, that your <hi>Cabal</hi> is of
marvellous uſe, for the giving Light to Antiquity. So marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous (reply'd he
Gravely) that without it, Scripture, Hiſtory, Fable, and Nature, are
obſcure and unintelligible. You believe, for Example, that the injury which
<hi>Cham</hi> did to his Father, was ſuch, as it ſeemes to be by the
Letter: Truly, it is clear ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing. <hi>Noah</hi> came out of the Ark,
and ſeeing that <hi>Veſta</hi> his Wife did nothing but trick up her
ſelf, for the Commerce which ſhe had with her Gallant <hi>Oromaſis,</hi>
becomes paſſionately in<pb n="120" facs="tcp:94889:65"/>love with her again;
<hi>Cham</hi> fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that his Father would ſtock the Earth with another
Race of people as black as his <hi>Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opians,</hi> took his opportunity one
day, when the good old Man was overcome with Wine, and Gelt him without Mercy.
Do you Laugh?</p>
               <p>I laugh at the indiſcreet Zeal of <hi>Cham.</hi> (Said I to
him) You ſhould rather admire (replied the <hi>Count</hi>) the goodneſs of
the Salamander <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> whoſe jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy did not hinder him from
pitying the diſgrace of his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val. He taught his Son <hi>Zora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
otherwiſe called <hi>Japhet,</hi> the Name of the Almighty God, which
expreſſes his Eternal Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundity: <hi>Japhet</hi> pronounced ſix times,
altervatively with his Brother <hi>Sem,</hi> going backward towards the
Patriarch, the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful name <hi>JABAMIAH;</hi> and ſo<pb n="121" facs="tcp:94889:65"/>they reſtored the old Man whole again. This Hiſtory, ill
under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the Greeks, made them ſay, that the Ancienteſt of the
Gods, had been Gelded by one of his Children: But here you ſee the truth of
the buſineſs. Where you may obſerve, how much in their morality, the
peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Fire are more Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane than ours, and indeed, exceeding that of
the people of the Air, or of the Water; For the Jealouſy of theſe is cruel,
as the Divine <hi>Paracelſus</hi> has ſhewn us in an Adventure which he
relates, and which was ſeen by all the People of the City of
<hi>Stauf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>femberg.</hi> A <hi>Phyloſopher,</hi> with whom a <hi>Nymph</hi>
was entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Commerce of Immortality, was ſo diſhoneſt a Man, as to
fall in Love with a <hi>Woman:</hi> But as he Dined with his new Miſtreſs,
and certain of his Friends, there<pb n="122" facs="tcp:94889:66"/>was ſeen in the Air,
the Loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Creature of the World; which was the Inviſible Lover, that
had a mind to let her ſelf be ſeen by the Friends of her unfaithful
Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant; that they might Judg how little reaſon he could have, to prefer a
<hi>Woman</hi> before her. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which the enraged <hi>Nymph</hi> ſtruck him
dead immediately.</p>
               <p>Ha! Sir, (cryed I) that might give me ſufficient Diſguſt
againſt theſe ſo Jealous Lovers. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, (purſued he) that their
Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy is a little violent. But if amongſt our <hi>Women,</hi> we have
ſeen enraged Lovers kill their perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Gallants; we ſhould not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
that theſe Lovers, ſo fair, and ſo faithful, are tranſported when they
are dealt falſly with: So much the more, in regard that they require Men but
to abſtain from <hi>Women,</hi> whoſe Defects they cannot abide; and that
they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit<pb n="123" facs="tcp:94889:66"/>us to Love amongſt them, as many as we
pleaſe. They pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Intereſt and Immortality of their Fellows, before
their own particular Satisfaction: And they are glad, that the <hi>Sages</hi>
give to their Republick ſo many Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Children, as they are able to
give.</p>
               <p>But pray, Sir, (demanded I) How comes it to paſs, that there
are ſo few Examples of all this which you tell me? There are a great number,
my Child (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered he) But Men make not a true Reflection, where they
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn not their Faith; where (I ſay) they explain it ill, for want of a
true Knowlede of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. They attribute to the <hi>Devils,</hi> all
that which ſhould be attributed to the People of the <hi>Elements.</hi> A
little <hi>Gnome</hi> got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Affections of the Famous <hi>Magdalen of
the Croſs,</hi> Abbeſs of<pb n="124" facs="tcp:94889:67"/>a <hi>Monaſtery</hi> at
<hi>Cordova</hi> in <hi>Spain;</hi> ſhe made him Happy, when ſhe was but
twelve Years old; and they continued their Commerce for the ſpace of thirty
Years: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til an Ignorant Director perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Magdalen,</hi> that her
Lover was a Fiend; and forced her to demand Abſolution of Pope <hi>Paul</hi>
the Third. Yet it is impoſſible, that this could be a <hi>Daemon:</hi> For
all <hi>Europe</hi> knew, and <hi>Caſſidorus Renius</hi> has made known to
all Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, the great Miracles which dayly were wrought in favor of this
Holy Woman; which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly had never come to paſs, if her Commerce with the
<hi>Gnome</hi> had been ſo Diabolick, as the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Director imagined.
The ſame Doctor would have affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very poſitively, if I am not
miſtaken, That the <hi>Sylphe</hi> who Immortalized himſelf with
<hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude,</hi> the young Religious <hi>Nun,</hi> 
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:94889:67"/>at
the <hi>Monaſtery</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> in the Dioeceſs of
<hi>Cologne,</hi> was ſome <hi>Devil.</hi> Truly, (ſaid I to him) ſo do I
too. Ah! my Son, (purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Count,</hi> ſmiling) if that were true,
the <hi>Devil</hi> would not be very miſerable; could he have the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to
entertain a Commerce of Gallantry with a pritty Wench of Thirteen Years old,
and write her Amorous Letters, which were found in her Cabinet.</p>
               <p>No, no, (my Child) Believe; that the <hi>Devil</hi> in his
Region of Death, has Employment more ſad, and more conformable to the Shame
which the <hi>God</hi> of Purity has ordain'd for him. But ſo it is, that Men
voluntarily ſhut their Eyes. We find, for example, in <hi>Titus Livius,</hi>
that <hi>Romulus</hi> was the Son of <hi>Mars:</hi> Your great Wits ſay, 'Tis
a Fable: Your Divines, That he was the Son of an <hi>Incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> The merry
Wags, That Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs<pb n="126" facs="tcp:94889:68"/>
                  <hi>Sylvia</hi> had loſt her
Gloves, and for an Excuſe to hide her Shame, gave out a Report, that the
<hi>God</hi> had ſtoln them. We, who know Nature, and whom <hi>God</hi> has
called from Darkneſs to this admirable Light; we know, that this pretended
<hi>Mars</hi> was a <hi>Salamander,</hi> who enamoured with the Young
<hi>Silvia,</hi> made her the Mother of <hi>Romulus.</hi> This <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roe,</hi>
who after he had founded his Magnificient City, was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed away by his Father
in a Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Chariot, as <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> was by <hi>Oramaſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another <hi>Salamander</hi> was the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Servius
Tullius. Titus Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> ſayes, That it was the <hi>God of Fire,</hi>
being deceived by the Reſemblance; and the Ignorants have followed the ſame
Opinion of it, as of the Father of <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi> The Famous
<hi>Hercules,</hi> the Invincible <hi>Alexander,</hi> were Sons 
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:94889:68"/>of ſome of the great <hi>Sylphs.</hi> The Hiſtorians
not knowing this, have ſaid, that <hi>Jupiter</hi> was their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. They
ſaid true: For as you have learnt; Theſe <hi>Sylphs Nymphs,</hi> and
<hi>Salamanders,</hi> being made Deities; The Hiſtorians, who believed them
ſo, call all thoſe who were born of them, <hi>Children of the
Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such was the Divine <hi>Plato,</hi> the more Divine
<hi>Apollonius Thianeus, Theſeus, Achilles, Sarpedon,</hi> the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<hi>Aeneas,</hi> and the Famous <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck:</hi> For, Do you know who
was the Father of <hi>Melchiſedeck?</hi> No truly, (ſaid I to him) for St.
<hi>Paul</hi> knew it not. Then ſay, that he would not tell it, (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
the <hi>Count</hi>) and that he was not permitted to reveal the <hi>Cabalistick
Myſteries.</hi> He knew well enough, that the Father of
<hi>Milchiſedeck</hi> was a <hi>Sylphe;</hi> and that the King of
<hi>Salem</hi> was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived<pb n="128" facs="tcp:94889:69"/>in the <hi>Ark,</hi> by the
Wife of <hi>Sem.</hi> The manner of this Prieſts ſacrifizing, was the
ſame which his Couſin <hi>Egeria</hi> taught King <hi>Numa;</hi> as alſo,
the Adoration of a Sovereign Divinity, without Image, and without Statue. For
which reaſon, the <hi>Romans</hi> becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Idolaters,</hi> ſometime
after burnt the Holy Books of <hi>Numa,</hi> which <hi>Egeria</hi> had
dictated. The firſt God of the <hi>Romans,</hi> was the True <hi>God;</hi>
Their Sacrifices were true: They offered Bread and Wine to the Soveraign
Maſter of the World: But all this was afterwards per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted. Nevertheleſs,
<hi>God</hi> was pleaſed, in reward of this firſt Worſhip, to give to
this City, which had acknowledged his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, the Empire of the
U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe. The ſame Sacrifice, which <hi>Melchiſedeck—</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I beſeech you, Sir, (interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted I) let us leave off this of
<hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedeck,</hi>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:94889:69"/>the <hi>Sylphe</hi> that begot
him, his Couſin <hi>Egeria,</hi> and the Sacrifice of Bread and Wine. Theſe
Examples are fetcht a far off; you would oblige me, would you produce ſome
Examples of a freſher Date: For I have heard a Doctor ſay, being asked what
was become of all the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of that <hi>Satyre,</hi> which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to
Saint <hi>Anthony,</hi> and which you call a <hi>Sylphe,</hi> That all thoſe
kind of People now are Dead. So all the Elementary People may poſſibly be
periſhed; ſince you affirm them to be Mortal, and that we hear no more News
of them.</p>
               <p>Would to <hi>God!</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Count</hi> in a Fury)
Would to <hi>God,</hi> that I knew nothing, that ſo I might keep this
Ignorant ſtill in his Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; who maintains ſo ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhly, what he
underſtands not! May <hi>God</hi> confound him, and all ſuch as he is!
Where has he<pb n="130" facs="tcp:94889:70"/>learnt, that the <hi>Elements</hi> are voyd?
and that theſe marvellous Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are reduced to their No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? Would he but
give him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the trouble to read a few Hiſtories, and not attribute to the
<hi>Devil,</hi> what is done by Nature; as the good Old Wives do all that,
which paſſes their <hi>Chymerick Theory;</hi> There would at all times, and
in all places, be found Proofs e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of what I am telling you.</p>
               <p>What would your Doctor ſay to this Authentick Hiſtory, which
happened not long ſince in <hi>Spain?</hi> A Beauteous <hi>Sylphide</hi> made
her ſelf be beloved by a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> lived three Years with him, had
three pretty Children by him, and then dyed. Muſt we ſay, that this was a
<hi>Devil?</hi> What a wiſe Anſwer would this be! Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what
Phyſicks, could the <hi>Devil</hi> organize the Body of a <hi>Woman,</hi>
Conceive, Bring-forth,<pb n="131" facs="tcp:94889:70"/>and give Suck? VVhat Proof is there
in the Scripture, of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Power, which your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines are obliged,
in this Rancoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to give to the <hi>Devil?</hi> And with what probable
Reaſon could their weak Phyſicks furniſh them? The <hi>Jeſuit
Delrio,</hi> being of a large Faith, relates at large, many of theſe
Adventures; and without troubling himſelf for Phyſical Reaſons,
diſpatches the Buſineſs in a word; ſaying, That theſe
<hi>Sylphides</hi> were <hi>Daemons:</hi> So true it is, that the greateſt
Doctors, do for the moſt part, know no more of them, than ſimple Women! So
true it is, that <hi>God</hi> is pleaſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire into his Cloudy Throne,
and thickning the darkneſs which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſeth his Omnipotent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,
he inhabits an inacceſſible Light, and lets not his Truths be ſeen but by
the humble of Heart. Learn to be Humble, my Son, if<pb n="132" facs="tcp:94889:71"/>you
would penetrate the ſacred Clouds, which environ Truth. Learn of the Sages
not to give to the <hi>Devil</hi>'s any power over na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſince the Fatal
ſtone has clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them in the Pits of the Abyſs. Learn of the
<hi>Pyhloſophers,</hi> to ſearch always after Natural cauſes, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
extraordinary Accident; and when Natural cauſes fail; have recourſe to God,
and to his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels, but never to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi>'s, who have no power
over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, but to ſuffer; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you will blaſpheme, many times
when you think not on't, and you will attribute to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> the
Honour of the moſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous works of nature.</p>
               <p>When you ſhall be told, for example, That the Divine
<hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Thianeus</hi> was conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the operation of any Man,
and that one of the moſt illuſtrious <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamanders</hi> deſcended to
immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize<pb n="133" facs="tcp:94889:71"/>himſelf with his Mother: Will you ſay that
this <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> was a <hi>Daemon,</hi> and will you aſcribe the
Glory to the <hi>Devil,</hi> of generating one of the greateſt Men, that ever
proceeded from our Phyloſophick Marriages.</p>
               <p>But Sir, (interrupted I) this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollonius,</hi> is reputed
amongſt us, for a great <hi>Sorcerer,</hi> and that is all the good they
ſay of him. Behold (proceeded the Count) one of the moſt admirable effects
of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ill Education! Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have heard our Nurſes, tell
us tales of Witches and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jures; whatſoever is done by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
means, muſt needs have the Devil for its Author. The great Doctors are at a
fine paſs, they ſhall not be believed, if they ſpake not as our Nurſes
do. <hi>Apollonius</hi> was not begot by a Man: He underſtood the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage
of Birds; He was ſeen in<pb n="134" facs="tcp:94889:72"/>two divers parts of the World in
one day: He vaniſhed from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Emperour <hi>Domitian,</hi> who would
have puniſhed him; He raiſed a Maid from the Dead, by vertue of
<hi>Onomancy;</hi> He told at <hi>Epheſus</hi> before an Aſſembly of all
<hi>Aſia,</hi> that at that very inſtant the Tyrant was kill'd at
<hi>Rome.</hi> How lies the queſtion to Judge of this Man? The Nurſe
ſays, that he is a <hi>Sorcerer;</hi> St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> and St.
<hi>Juſtin</hi> the <hi>Martyr</hi> ſay, that he was but a great
<hi>Philoſopher: Jerom, Juſtin,</hi> and our <hi>Cabaliſts,</hi> they
muſt be Phantaſticks; and the ſilly VVoman muſt carry it. Ha! Let the
Ignorant periſh in his Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: But you, my Child, ſave your ſelf from
the Shipwrack.</p>
               <p>VVhen you ſhall read that the famous <hi>Merlin,</hi> was born
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the operation of any Man, of a Religious VVoman, the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the
King of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:94889:72"/>and that he foretold what
ſhould come to paſs, more clearly than ever <hi>Tyreſias</hi> did; Say
not with the People, that he was the Son of an <hi>Incubus,</hi> ſince it was
no ſuch thing; nor did he ever prophecy by the art of the Devil: Becauſe
the Devil is the moſt ignorant of all Creatures, according to the Holy
<hi>Cabal.</hi> Say with the <hi>Sages,</hi> that the <hi>Brittiſh</hi>
Princeſs was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in her Solitude, by a <hi>Sylph,</hi> who had pitty
on her: that he took care to divert her, that he knew how to pleaſe her, and
that <hi>Merlin</hi> their Son, was Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by the <hi>Sylph,</hi> in all the
<hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Sciences,</hi> and taught by him to do all the Marvels, which the
ſtory of <hi>England</hi> relates of him.</p>
               <p>Nor muſt you do injury to the <hi>Earls of Cleave,</hi> to
ſay that the <hi>Devil</hi> is their Father: And have a better Opinion of the
<hi>Sylphe,</hi> of whom the Hiſtory ſayes, that<pb n="136" facs="tcp:94889:73"/>he
came to <hi>Cleve</hi> in a Miraculous Ship, drawn by a <hi>Swan,</hi> who was
tyed to it by a Silver Chain. This Sylphe, after he had divers Children by the
Heireſs of <hi>Cleve,</hi> went away at Noon-day, in the ſight of a VVorld
of People, in his Airy Ship. VVhat has he done to your Doctors, that ſhould
make them rank him amongſt the <hi>Devils?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But will you likewiſe handle ſo roughly the honour of the
Houſe of <hi>Luſignan?</hi> And will you give a Diabolick Genealogy to the
<hi>Earls of Poitiers?</hi> what will you ſay to their renowned Mother? I
Believe Sir, (interrupted I) that you are going about to tell me the tale of
<hi>Meluſina.</hi> Nay, If you deny the Hiſtory of <hi>Meluſina,</hi>
(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed he) I have done with you. If you deny that, I ſay, we muſt burn
the Books of the great <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus,</hi> who maintains in five or 
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:94889:73"/>ſix ſeveral places, that there is nothing more
certain, than that this <hi>Meluſina</hi> was a <hi>Nymph;</hi> and you
muſt alſo give your Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans the Lye, who ſay, that ſince her
Death, or to ſpeak more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, ſince ſhe diſappeared from the eyes
of her Husband, ſhe has ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver failed (at all times when any of her
poſterity have been threatned by ſome misfortune, or that ſome <hi>King
of France</hi> ſhould dye in any extraordinary manner) to appear in Mourning,
upon the great Tower of the Caſtle of <hi>Luſignan,</hi> which ſhe had
cauſed to be built. You will have a quarrel with all thoſe who are
deſcended from this <hi>Nymph,</hi> or who are allied to this Family; if you
are obſtinate to maintain that this was a <hi>Devil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Think you Sir (ſaid I to him) that theſe Lords are any thing
more pleaſed, to deduce their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digree from the <hi>Sylphs?</hi> They 
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:94889:74"/>would be better pleaſed, without doubt (replyed he) if
they knew that which I teach you; and they would eſteem for a great honour
theſe extraordinary Births. They would know, if they had any Light of the
<hi>Cabal,</hi> that this way of Generation, being more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the
manner, by which God intended in the beginning, that the World ſhould be
mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed; the Children which ſhould ſo be born are more happy, more
valiant, more wiſe, more renowned, and more bleſt by God. Is it not more
Glorious for theſe Illuſtrious Men to deſcend from theſe Creatures ſo
perfect, ſo pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and ſo powerfull, than from ſome foul Fiend, or
ſome infamous <hi>Aſmodeus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir, (ſaid I to him) our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines will not ſay, That the
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> is the Father of all thoſe Men, who are born without our 
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:94889:74"/>knowing who put them into the World. They acknowledge,
that the <hi>Devil</hi> is a Spirit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not able to beget.
<hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Nicene,</hi> (continued the <hi>Count</hi>) ſayes not
ſo, for he is of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the <hi>Devils</hi> multiply a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
themſelves, as Men do. VVe are not of his mind, (repli'd I) but it happens
(ſay our Doctors) that—Hold! Do not ſay (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted the
<hi>Count</hi>) Do not ſay, what they ſay; for, you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as they
do, a very ſottiſh, and very diſhoneſt Notion. What an abominable
defeat have they found out? 'Tis an aſtoniſhment to think, how they have
all una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly embraced this filthy Conceit, and how they have ordinarily
taken pleaſure, to poſt from Whimſeys to impoſtures, to profit the lazy
Brutality of ſuch as devoted themſelves to Solitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and quickly to
advance the<pb n="140" facs="tcp:94889:75"/>Fame of theſe miraculous Men in the World,
whoſe illuſtrious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory they Celebrate from ſo vile an Original. Do
they call this Philoſophizing? Is it worthy of <hi>God,</hi> to ſay, that
he has this kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the <hi>Devil,</hi> to countenance theſe
abominations, to allow them the favour of being Fruitful, which has been
refuſed to the greateſt Saints, and to recompence theſe Fiends, by
Creating for theſe Embrios of iniquity, more He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roique Souls, then for
thoſe who have been formed in the Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Legitimate marriage? Is it
not a diſparagement to ſay with your Doctors, that the <hi>Devil</hi> can
by this deteſtable Artifice: make a Virgin conceive during her ſleep,
without any prejudice to her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity? Which is as abſurd as the ſtory
which <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> (otherwiſe a moſt Solid Author, and who knew
a little of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi>)<pb n="141" facs="tcp:94889:75"/>forgetting himſelf,
relates in his Sixteenth <hi>Quodlibet,</hi> of a Maid that lay with her
Father, to whom he makes the ſame happen, as ſome of the <hi>Heretick
Rabins</hi> ſay, happened to the Daughter of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> whom they
make to conceive the great Cabaliſt <hi>Ben-Syrach,</hi> only by going into
the Bath after the Prophet. I ſhould judg, that this impertinence was
imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by ſome—</p>
               <p>Give me leave, Sir, to interrupt your declamation (ſaid I to
him) I proteſt, that, to appeaſe you, I could wiſh our Doctors had
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived ſome other Solution, by which ſuch pure Ears as yours, might be
leſſe offended: Or elſe they ſhould have utterly denyed the matter, on
which the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is founded.</p>
               <p>What an Admirable expedient (replyed the <hi>Count</hi>) have
you thought upon, which is to deny<pb n="142" facs="tcp:94889:76"/>real things! Put the
caſe that you were one of theſe great Doctors, with your Gown lined with
<hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> and ſuppoſe that the Bleſſed <hi>Danhuzerus,</hi> came
to you as to the Oracle of his Religion—</p>
               <p>At this moment, up came a Laquey to tell me, that a young Lord
was come to viſit me. I would not have him ſee me by any means. (ſaid the
<hi>Count</hi>) I beg your pardon Sir, (ſaid I to him) You may gueſs, by
this Lords Name, that there is no ſhifting him off, if I ſhould ſend him
word that I am not to be ſpoken with. Be pleaſed therefore to give your
ſelf the trouble of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into that ſtudy. 'Tis no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (ſaid he) I
will make my ſelf inviſible. Ah! Sir, (cry'd I) No witchcraft, I beſeech
you, I do not underſtand that Sport. What ignorance is it, (ſaid the
<hi>Count,</hi> Laughing and ſhrugging up his<pb n="143" facs="tcp:94889:76"/>ſhoulders) not to know, that to be inviſible, is but to put before
ones ſelf, ſomething contrary to the light! He went into my ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and
the young Lord came, almoſt at the ſame inſtant, into my Chamber: Of whom
I Craved pardon, that I did not waite upon him up.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="discourse">
               <head>Diſcourſe the Fifth.</head>
               <p>THe great Lord being gone, and I come back from wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on him
to his Coach, found the <hi>Count of Gabalis</hi> in my Chamber. 'Tis a great
loſs to us: (ſaid he to me) that this Lord who has now taken his leave of
you, muſt one day come to<pb n="144" facs="tcp:94889:77"/>be one of the Seventy two
Princes of the <hi>Sanhadrin</hi> of the new Law; had it not been for that, he
would have been a worthy Subject for our holy <hi>Cabal;</hi> He has a Wit
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, quaint, vaſt, ſublime, and bold. Look here upon the <hi>Figure
of Geomancy,</hi> which I have caſt for him, during the time that you have
been talking together. I never ſaw Happyer Points, and ſuch as marked out
ſo fair a Soul.</p>
               <p>Behold this 
<note n="*" place="margin">Terms of
Geomancy.</note>
                  <hi>MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER,</hi> VVhat Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity ſhe gives him? This 
<note n="*" place="margin">Terms of
Geomancy.</note>
                  <hi>DAUGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER</hi> will procure the Purple for him. I wiſh
ill to him, and his Fortune; For this reaſon, that it takes from Phyloſophy
a Subject, which perchance may ſurpaſs you. But, where were we, when he
came?</p>
               <p>You ſpeak to me, Sir, (ſaid I) of a Bleſſed Perſon,
whom I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<pb n="145" facs="tcp:94889:77"/>ſaw in all the <hi>Roman Callen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> I
think you called him <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huzerus.</hi> Tis true, (purſued he) I remember
it. I was ſaying to you, that you ſhould put your ſelf in the place of
one of your Doctors, and ſuppoſe, that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Danhuzerus</hi>
came to lay open to you his Conſcience, and ſay to you:</p>
               <p>Sir, I come from beyond the <hi>Alps</hi> to wait on you, at the
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of your Wiſdome; I have a little ſcruple, which gives me ſome
trouble of Conſcience. There is in a mountaine of <hi>Italy,</hi> a
<hi>Nymph</hi> who keeps her Court there: a thouſand <hi>Nymphs</hi> ſerve
her, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as Beautiful as ſhe; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe handſome Men, very wiſe,
and very honeſt perſons. Thither they come from all the Habitable Earth;
they love theſe <hi>Nymphs,</hi> and are beloved by them: There they lead the
ſweeteſt life of the World.<pb n="146" facs="tcp:94889:78"/>They have moſt beautiful
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by thoſe whom they love. They worſhip the living <hi>God:</hi>
They hurt no Man; And they hope for Immortality. I walked one day up this
mountain, and pleaſed the Queen of the <hi>Nymphs:</hi> ſhe became
viſible and ſhewed me her Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Court. The <hi>Sages,</hi> who
perceived that ſhe loved me, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected me almoſt, as if I had been their
Prince: They exhort me to liſten and yeild my ſelf to the Sighs and Beauty
of the <hi>Nymph.</hi> She relates her paſſion to me; Nor forgets ſhe any
thing, that may touch my heart: And in fine, declares that ſhe ſhall die,
if I will not Love her; and that, if I will love her, ſhe will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,
her ſelf obliged to me for her Immortality. The Reaſons of thoſe Wiſe
men, have convinced my Spirit, and the Attractions of the <hi>Nymph</hi> have 
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:94889:78"/>gained my heart. I love, I have very hopefull Children by
her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But in the midſt of my Felicity, I am ſometimes troubled, when I
remember, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> does not at all approve of this. I
come therefore, to you, Sir, to conſult you, that I may know, what this
<hi>Nymph,</hi> theſe <hi>Sages,</hi> theſe <hi>Children,</hi> may be; and
in what eſtate is my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Come on, now Maſter Doctor, what
anſwer will you make to the Lord <hi>Danhuze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would ſay to him, (anſwered I.) My Lord
<hi>Danhuzerus,</hi> ſaving the Reſpect which I owe you; You are a little
mad, or elſe, your Viſion is Witchcraft; Your Children, and your
Miſtreſſe, are filthy Fiends; and I am of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that your
Conſcience is ſeared to ſome purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:94889:79"/>With this Anſwer, my Child, you might
very well merit a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's Cap: But never to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into our Society
(conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the <hi>Count,</hi> with a great Sigh). Behold the barbarous
Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of all the Doctors of this Age! A poor <hi>Sylphe</hi> dares
not ſhew his Head amongſt us, but he is preſently taken for a Fiend. A
<hi>Nymph</hi> cannot labor to become Immortal, without paſſing for an
unclean Spirit: And a <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> muſt not ſhew himſelf, leſt
he be accounted a <hi>Devil;</hi> and the pure Flames, which compoſe him, for
Hell-Fire, which he carryes along with him. They have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived, that they may
diſpel theſe Suſpicions, to make the Signe of the <hi>Croſs,</hi> when
they ſhall appear; Kneel down before the Divine Names, and pronounce them
too, with Reverence: And yet all theſe Precautions are vain. Nor 
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:94889:79"/>can all your Tricks ever procure, that they ſhould be
reputed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>God,</hi> whom they Adore more Religiouſly, than
thoſe who fly from them.</p>
               <p>Very good, Sir, (ſaid I to him) You think, it ſeems, that
theſe People are wondrous Devout like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Very Devout, (anſwered he)
and very Zealous for the <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> The excellent Diſcourſes, which
they make of the <hi>Divine Eſſence,</hi> and their admirable Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, do
greatly Edify us. Have they Prayers too? (ſaid I to him) I ſhould be glad
to ſee One of their making. 'Tis eaſie to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy you, (replyed he)
and to the end, that I may clear you from having any ſuſpicion, and that
you may not ſuſpect me for the Contriver of it: Liſten to that, which the
<hi>Salamander,</hi> who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the Temple of <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi> taught
the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and which<pb n="150" facs="tcp:94889:80"/>
                  <hi>Porphyrius</hi> relates.
It contains ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime <hi>Theology:</hi> And you will ſee by it, that he
received not from theſe <hi>Sage</hi> Creatures, any other Doctrine, than
that the World ſhould Worſhip the onely True <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>THE <hi>Salamander</hi>'s Prayer.</head>
                           <p>IMmortal, Eternal, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpeakable, and Sacred
<hi>Father</hi> of all Things! who art carryed upon the Chariots of the
Spheres, which alwayes rowl about. Ruler over the Etherial Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, where the
Throne of thy Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is raiſed: from the high Top of which, Thine
all-piercing Eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold All, and thy pure and holy Ears hear All. Help thy
Children, whom thou hast loved from the Birth of Ages. For thy Bright, thy
Great, and Eternal Majeſty, ſhines above<pb n="151" facs="tcp:94889:80"/>the Earth, the
Heavens, and the Stars. Thou art raiſed above them, Oh th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                                 <desc>•…</desc>
                              </gap> ſparkling Fire! There thou giveſt
Light, and entertaineſt thy Self with thine own Splendor; and from thy
Eſſence, flow forth Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Rivers of Light, which nouriſh thy Infinit
Spirit. This Infinit Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit produceth all Things; and makes this
inexhauſtible Treaſure of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which can never fail the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration,
which alwayes compaſſeth it about; by reaſon of the number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Forms,
with which it is preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and with which thou haſt fill'd it at the
Beginning. From this Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, do theſe moſt Holy Kings, alſo draw their
original, who are round about thy Throne, and who compoſe thy Court. O Father
univerſal! O Thou Holy One! O Father of Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Mortals, and Immortals!
Thou haſt particularly created Powers, who are marvellouſly like to Thine
eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Thought, and to Thy adorable<pb n="152" facs="tcp:94889:81"/>Eſſence: Thou
haſt eſtabliſhed them above the Angels, who declare thy Will to the
World. In fine, Thou hast created Us a third ſort of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, in the
Elements. Our conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Exerciſe, is to praiſe Thee, and to adore Thy
Diſpenſations. We burn with the Deſire of poſſeſſing Thee. O
Father! O Mother, the tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest of Mothers! O admirable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, of the
Paſſions and Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mothers! O Son, the Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of all Sons! O
Form of all Forms! Soul, Spirit, Harmony, and Number of all Things!</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>What ſay you to this Prayer of the <hi>Salamanders?</hi> Is it
not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Wiſe, very Lofty, and very Devout? And likewiſe very Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure,
(anſwered I) I once heard a Preacher paraphraſe upon this; and he proved by
it, that the <hi>Devil,</hi> beſides the other Vices which he has, is above
all, a great Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite.<pb n="153" facs="tcp:94889:81"/>Alas! (cryed the <hi>Count</hi>)
Then, What Recourſe have ye, to betake your ſelves to, O ye poor Elementary
People! Ye tell Marvels of the Nature of <hi>God,</hi> Of the <hi>Father,</hi>
Of the <hi>Son,</hi> Of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> Of the Aſſiſtant
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences, Of Angels, and Of the Heavens! Ye make admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prayers, and
ye teach them to Men: And yet after all, ye are but Fiends and Hypocrites!</p>
               <p>Sir, (interrupted I) you do me no pleaſure at all, in
invoking, on this manner, this ſort of People. Alas, my Son! (continued he)
Be not troubled, that I call upon them; but that your weakneſs hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders you
from admiring hereafter, that you ſaw not ſo many <hi>Examples,</hi> as you
will wiſh you had done, of their Alliance with Men. Alas! Where is the Women,
whoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination your Doctors have not Corrupted; ſo much, as that 
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:94889:82"/>ſhe thinks not but with Horror, on this Commerce; and
trembles at the very Aſpect of a <hi>Sylphe?</hi> Where is the Man, who flyes
not from the Sight of them, if he pretends but never ſo little to be a
virtuous honeſt Man? How rarely do we find a Man of worth, who deſires
their Familiarity? Nor are there any but Debauched Perſons, or Covetous, or
Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or Impoſtors, who ſeek for this Honour; which yet they ſhall
never attain to, I aſſure you: For, <hi>The Fear of the Lord, is the
Beginning of Wiſdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What then (ſaid I) ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of all theſe Airy People,
ſince all ſuch as are Honeſt, are ſo ſet againſt them? Well,
(ſaid he) <hi>The Arme of</hi> God <hi>is not ſhortned;</hi> and the
<hi>Devil</hi> ſhall not draw to himſelf, all the Advantages, he hopes for,
from the Ignorance and Error, which he has vented to<pb n="155" facs="tcp:94889:82"/>their
prejudice: For beſides the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> who are a great number,
and remedy it the beſt they can, by utterly Renouncing <hi>Women; God</hi>
has permitted all theſe People, to uſe all Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Arts, which they can
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive, to converſe with Men, without their Knowledge. What do you tell
me, Sir? (cryed I) I tell you Truth, (purſued he) Do you believe, that a
<hi>Dog</hi> may have Children by a Woman? No, (anſwered I.) Nor a
<hi>Munky?</hi> (added he) Neither, (replyed I.) Nor a <hi>Bear?</hi>
(continued he) Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dog,</hi> nor <hi>Munkey,</hi> nor <hi>Bear,</hi>
(ſaid I to him.) For that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, without all doubt: 'Tis
againſt Nature, againſt Reaſon, and againſt Common Senſe. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good,
(ſaid the <hi>Count</hi>) But are not the Kings of the <hi>Goths,</hi>
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from a <hi>Bear,</hi> and a <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> Princeſs? 'Tis
true, (ſaid I)<pb n="156" facs="tcp:94889:83"/>the Hiſtory ſayes it. And were not the
<hi>Peguſians,</hi> and <hi>Syonians</hi> of <hi>India,</hi> (reply'd he)
Born from a <hi>Dog,</hi> and a <hi>Woman?</hi> I have read that too, (ſaid I
to him.) And had not that <hi>Portugeſs</hi> Woman, (continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he) who was
expoſed in a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart <hi>Iſland,</hi> Children by a great
<hi>Munkey?</hi> Our Divines, Sir, (ſaid I) anſwer to that, That the
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> taking the Shape of theſe Beaſts—You are going to
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge again, (interrupted the <hi>Count</hi>) the Nonſenſical
Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of your Authors. Pray, comprehend once for all, that the
<hi>Sylphes,</hi> ſeeing themſelves taken for <hi>Devils,</hi> when they
appear in Human Shape, to diminiſh this Averſion, which is had againſt
them, take the Shapes of theſe Beaſts; and ſo addreſs themſelves to
the wanton Frailty of <hi>Women;</hi> who are affrighted at a Lovely
<hi>Sylphide,</hi> but not at a <hi>Dog,</hi> or<pb n="157" facs="tcp:94889:83"/>
                  <hi>Munkey.</hi> I could tell you many Tales of your little
<hi>Bolognian Dogs,</hi> and certain pretty <hi>Ladyes</hi> in the World: But I
have a greater Secret to teach you.</p>
               <p>Know, my Son, that many a one thinks himſelf the Son of a
<hi>Man,</hi> who is the Son of a <hi>Sylphe.</hi> Another thinks, that he is
in Bed with his <hi>Wife;</hi> and without ever knowing it, he Immortalized a
<hi>Sylphe.</hi> This <hi>Woman</hi> ſuppoſes, that ſhe is Embracing her
<hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band;</hi> and ſhe is Hugging be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt her Arms, a
<hi>Salamander:</hi> And that <hi>Girle</hi> durſt ſwear when ſhe awakes,
that ſhe is a <hi>Virgin;</hi> that has had in her Sleep, an Honour that
ſhe little dreamt on. So the <hi>Devil,</hi> and the <hi>Ignorants,</hi> are
equally abuſed.</p>
               <p>Well, (ſaid I) But could not the <hi>Devil</hi> awaken that
ſleeping Maid, to hinder this <hi>Salamander</hi> from becoming Immortal? He 
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:94889:84"/>could do it, (replyed the <hi>Count</hi>) if the
<hi>Sages</hi> did not take an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for that: But we teach all theſe
People, the way to bind the <hi>Devils,</hi> and to make Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to their
ſubtil Endeavours. Did I not tell you, the other day, That the
<hi>Sylphes,</hi> and the other Lords of the Elements, were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Happy, when
we ſhewed them the <hi>Cabal?</hi> Were it not for us, the <hi>Devil,</hi>
their great Enemy, would ſorely diſquiet them; and they would be hard put
to it, to Immortalize themſelves, without the Maids knowing it.</p>
               <p>I cannot (replyed I) ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admire the profound
Ignorance we live in: We always believed, that the Powers of the Air, do often
aſſiſt Lovers, in attaining what they deſired: And it ſeems, the
thing is clearly otherwiſe; For the Powers of the Air, have need of the
Aſſiſtance of Men, to ſerve<pb n="159" facs="tcp:94889:84"/>them in their Amours.
'Tis juſt as you ſay, my Son, (purſued the <hi>Count</hi>) The
<hi>Sages</hi> give Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour to theſe poor People; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them, Alas, too
unhappy, and too feeble, to reſiſt the <hi>Devil:</hi> For, when a
<hi>Sylphe</hi> has learnt of us, to pronounce Cabaliſtickly the powerful
Name of <hi>NEH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAHMIHAH;</hi> and to joyne in form, with the moſt delicious
Name <hi>ELIAEL,</hi> all the Powers of Darkneſs, take their Flight; and the
<hi>Sylphe</hi> enjoyes peacably, that which he Loves.</p>
               <p>So was that ingenious <hi>Sylphe</hi> immortalized, who took
upon him the ſhape of the Lover of a Lady of <hi>Sevil;</hi> The Hiſtory is
well enough known. The Young <hi>Spaniſh Lady</hi> was faire; but as Cruel,
as Fair. A <hi>Caſtillian Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who loved her to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
took a Reſolution one morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to leave her, without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:94889:85"/>to her; and to Travel, till ſuch time as he ſhould be
cured of his unprofitable paſſion. A <hi>Sylphe</hi> finding this <hi>Faire
one</hi> to his likeing, thought it his beſt courſe, to lay hold on this
opportunity; and Arming himſelf with all that, which one of our
<hi>Sages</hi> had taught him, to defend himſelf with, againſt the
Stratagems, which the <hi>Devil,</hi> envious of his good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, might
contrive for the diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing him. He goes to ſee the Gentlewoman taking
the ſhape of her abſent Lover. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines, ſighs, and is repulſed:
He preſſes, he Sollicites, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveres. After many Months, he works
upon her, makes himſelf beloved; he perſwades; and in ſhort, is happy.
There was born from their Loves, a Son, whoſe Birth was kept ſecret; and
the Addreſſe of this Aeryal Lover, managed privately, from the 
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:94889:85"/>knowledge of her Parents. The Love continues; and ſhe is
bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a ſecond Great Belly. In the mean time, the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
cured by Abſence, comes back, to <hi>Sevil;</hi> and impatient to ſee his
inhumane Miſtreſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, makes all the haſt he could to tell her;
That at laſt, he is in a condition of Diſpleaſing her no more; and that
he is come to declare to her, that he had done Loving her.</p>
               <p>Imagine, if you pleaſe, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment of this young
Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; Her Tears, her Reproaches, and their Surprizing Dialogue: She affirmes,
that ſhe has made him happy: Which he denys, And would have reminded him,
that their Child was in ſuch a place; that he is the Father of it; and that
ſhe is bigg of another, which he is alſo Father of. He is obſtinate, to
diſown all. She<pb n="162" facs="tcp:94889:86"/>Throws her ſelf againſt the ground,
and Teares her Haires: The Parents come running in at her Crys, the deſperate
Lover continues her Complaints, and Invectives. The Gentleman pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces
Teſtimony, that he had been abſent the ſpace of two years. The firſt
Child is ſought for, and found; and the ſecond was born in the right
Term.</p>
               <p>And what part plaid the Airy-Lover, (interrupted I) all this
while? I ſee well enough, (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the <hi>Count</hi>) that you are
diſpleaſed, that he ſhould forſake his Miſtreſſe, leaving her to
the Rigour of her Parents, and to the Fury of the Inquiſitors. But he had
reaſon to complain of her: She was not devout enough; for when theſe
Gentlemen immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize themſelves, they work ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and live very
holily; That they looſe not the Right, which they<pb n="163" facs="tcp:94889:86"/>came to
acquire of Soveraign good: So they would have the perſon, to whom they are
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied, live with exemplary inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; as may be ſeen, in that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
Adventure of <hi>A Young Lord of Bavaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was not to be comforted for the Death of his Wife, whom he
loved paſſionatly; A <hi>Sylphide</hi> was adviſed by one of our
<hi>Sages,</hi> to take upon her the ſhape of this Woman: She was
perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it, and preſents her ſelf to the afflicted young Man,
ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; That <hi>God</hi> had raiſed her from the dead again, to comfort
him in his extream Affliction. They live together many years, and had many
Lovely Children together: But the young Man was not ſo honeſt, as he
ſhould be, to retain his diſcreet <hi>Sylphide.</hi> He ſwore, and
ſpoke lewd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil Words: She reproved him<pb n="164" facs="tcp:94889:87"/>ſometimes.
But ſeeing that her Cautions were unprofitable, ſhe vaniſhed one day from
him, and left him nothing but her Gloaths, and the Repentance of his not having
followed her Holy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. Thus you ſee (my Son) that the <hi>Sylphes</hi>
have ſometimes reaſon to vaniſh away: And you ſee, that the
<hi>Devil</hi> cannot hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, any more than your Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Doctors, the
People of the <hi>Elements,</hi> that they ſhould not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, with
ſucceſs, to their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, when they are aſſiſted by ſome of
our <hi>Sages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, in good earneſt, Sir, (ſaid I) Are you perſwaded,
that the <hi>Devil</hi> is ſo great an Enemy, to theſe Suborners of Pretty
<hi>Matdens?</hi> A mortal Enemy, (ſaid the <hi>Count</hi>) eſpecially to
<hi>Sylphes, Nymphs,</hi> and <hi>Salamanders.</hi> But, as for the
<hi>Gnomes</hi> or <hi>Pharyes,</hi> he does not hate them ſo much, becauſe
they, as I<pb n="165" facs="tcp:94889:87"/>believe, you have heard ſay, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted by
the Terrible diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the <hi>Devil's</hi> make in the Center of
the Earth, chooſe rather to live Mortals, than run the Riſque of being ſo
Tormented, if they ſhould acquire Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Hence it comes to paſs,
that the <hi>Gnomes,</hi> and the <hi>Devil's</hi> their Neighbours, have a
very great Commerce. They per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade theſe <hi>Gnomes,</hi> who are
na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally great Friends of Man, that it is to do him great ſervice, and to
deliver him from great perril, in obliging him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce this Immortality.
By this, they ingage them to furniſh him, whom they can perſwade to this
Renunciation, with all the mony which he ſhall demand; To prevent the
dangers, which might threaten his life, during a certain time, or ſome ſuch
other Condition, as ſhall beſt pleaſe<pb n="166" facs="tcp:94889:88"/>the Man or
Woman, with whom they make this unhappy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact. So the <hi>Devil,</hi> wicked
as he is, by his Treaty with this <hi>Gnome,</hi> makes the Soul of a man
become Mortal, and deprives it of the right of Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>How Sir! (cryed I) Theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts, in your opinion, of which
the <hi>Demonographes</hi> relate ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples, are they not with the
<hi>Devil?</hi> No ſurely (continued the <hi>Count</hi>) has not the Prince
of the World, been chaſed out of it? Is he not ſhut up? Is he not bound? Is
he not curſed and damned from off the earth, and Throne down to remain at the
bottom of the work of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Architect; can he mount up into the Region
of Light, and there make his concentred Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs reſplendant? No, He can
do nothing againſt man. He can<pb n="167" facs="tcp:94889:88"/>only inſpire the
<hi>Gnomes,</hi> who are his Neighbours, to make theſe propoſitions to
ſuch men whom he moſt fears may be ſaved, to the end that their Soul may
die with their Body.</p>
               <p>Then do you believe, (added I) that the Souls dye? They dye, My
Child (anſwered he). And thoſe who make theſe compacts (purſued I) are
not they damned? They cannot be (ſaid he) for their Soul dies with their
body. They are quitted then at an eaſie rate (continued I) and are but
ſlightly puniſhed for having committed ſo Enormous a Crime, as renouncing
their Baptiſme, and the death of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Do you eſteem it (replyed the <hi>Count</hi>) a ſlight
puniſhment to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter into the Black Abyſs of Nothing? Know that it is a
far greater pain, than to be damned; for there is ſtill a remainder of 
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:94889:89"/>Mercy, in the Juſtice which God exerciſes againſt
ſinners in Hell. Since it is a great favour not to conſume them in the Fire
which burns them. To be Nothing, is a greater Miſery, than to be in
<hi>Hell:</hi> This is the Doctrine, which the <hi>Sages</hi> Preach to the
<hi>Gnomes,</hi> when they call them together, to make them underſtand, what
an Injury they do themſelves, to prefer Death before Immortality; and
Nothing, before the Hope of Eternal Happyneſs; which they juſtly might lay
claim to, if they would ally themſelves with men, and not Solicite theſe
Criminal Renunciations. Some of them who believe, we marry to our
Daughters.</p>
               <p>Do you preach the Goſpel then to theſe Subteranean people?
Sir (ſaid I to him). Why ſhould we not? (replyed he) We are their Doctors,
as well as of the<pb n="169" facs="tcp:94889:89"/>other People of the <hi>Fire,</hi> of the
<hi>Air,</hi> and of the <hi>Water:</hi> For the <hi>Philoſophick
Charity,</hi> is extended indifferently to all the Children of <hi>God.</hi>
For, as they are now ſubtil, and more clear, than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Children of
Men; ſo are they more Docible, and more capable of Diſcipline, &amp;
liſten to the Divine Truths, with an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and Reſpect which
aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes us.</p>
               <p>It muſt needs be a Raviſhing Sight, (ſaid I, ſmiling) to
ſee a <hi>Roſy-Cruſian Philoſopher,</hi> in a Chair preaching to all
theſe little Gentle-Folke. You ſhall have the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of it, my Son,
when you pleaſe, (ſaid the <hi>Count.</hi>) And if you deſire it, I will
aſſemble them this very Evening, and Preach to them at Midnight. At
Midnight (cryed I!) I have heard ſay, that That is the Hour of their
<hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi> At this the <hi>Count</hi> fell a<pb n="170" facs="tcp:94889:90"/>Laughing: You put me in mind (ſaid he) of all the Fooleries, which
<hi>Demonographers</hi> relate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Buſineſs of their
Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary <hi>Sabbath.</hi> I could wiſh, for the rarity of the Conceipt,
that you would believe them too.</p>
               <p>Alas! For thoſe Tales of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> (replyed I) I
do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve one of them. You do well, my Son, (ſaid he) for (once more I
muſt tell you) the <hi>Devil</hi> has not the Power to ſport himſelf ſo
with Mankind, nor to treat or correſpond with them; much<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, to make
himſelf Adored, as the <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> believe. That which has given
Riſe to this Popular Report, is, That the <hi>Sages</hi> (as I have been
telling you) aſſembling the Inhabitants of the <hi>Elements,</hi> to Preach
to them the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of the <hi>Secret Sciences,</hi> and their
<hi>Morality:</hi> And as it ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happens, that ſome <hi>Gnome,</hi> 
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:94889:90"/>being convinced of his groſs Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and apprehending
the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of being reduced to Nothing, conſents to his Immortalization:
Then has he a pritty Maid given him, is Marryed; and the Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Celebrated
with all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſo great a Conqueſt, as has then newly been
made, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. Theſe are thoſe Revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and Tokens of Joy, which
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays, were heard in certain <hi>Iſlands;</hi> where
nevertheleſs, they could not ſee any Body. The Great <hi>Orpheus</hi> was
the firſt, who convocated the <hi>Subterranean Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> At his firſt
Sermon, <hi>Sabaſius</hi> the Antienteſt of the <hi>Gnomes,</hi> was
Immortalized; And it was from this <hi>Sabaſius,</hi> that this Aſſembly
took its Name; in which the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> addreſſed their Diſcourſes
to him, ſo long as he Lived: As it appears in the <hi>Hymns</hi> of the
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Orpheus.</hi> The Ignorant have<pb n="172" facs="tcp:94889:91"/>confounded
theſe Things; and taken occaſion to make a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Impertinent Stories,
and to deſcribe an Aſſembly, which we convoque not, but to the Glory of
the <hi>Soveraign Being.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I did never imagine, that this <hi>Sabbath</hi> (ſaid I to
him) had been an Aſſembly for <hi>Devotion:</hi> Yet it is (continued he) a
moſt Holy, and moſt <hi>Cabaliſtick</hi> one: Which the World will not
eaſily be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to. But ſuch is the Deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Blindneſs of this
unjuſt Age, that Men ſtill do beſot themſelves with a vulgar Report,
&amp; will not ſuffer themſelves to be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. The <hi>Sages</hi> have
a fine time of it that the <hi>Sots</hi> are believed before them. A
<hi>Philoſopher</hi> would have a worthy Task, to take a Survey of all the
abſurd Falſities, and <hi>Chymaeras,</hi> which have been forged; and to
give manifeſt Proofs againſt them. For, whatſoever Experience, or 
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:94889:91"/>whatſoever ſolid Reaſon he might imploy, Should
there but come a Man in a Square Cap, and write underneath, <hi>This is
Falſe;</hi> Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and Demonſtration have no more Force; and it is no
more in the Power of Truth, to Re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh its Empire: Men will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
this Square Cap, before their own Eyes.</p>
               <p>The Famous Cabaliſt <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias,</hi> was moved in his
Spirit, in the Reign of your King <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin,</hi> to Convince the World, that
the <hi>Elements</hi> are Inhabited by all theſe People, whoſe Nature I
have been deſcribing to you. The Expedient to bring all this about, was in
this manner; He adviſed the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> to ſhew themſelves in the
Air to all the World. They did it with great Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence: Theſe Creatures
appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Air, in Human Shape; Sometimes ranged in Battle, 
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:94889:92"/>Marching in good Order, or ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Arms, or
Encamped under moſt Majeſtick Pavillions: At other times, on Airy Ships of
an Admirable Structure, whoſe Flying Navy was toſt about at the Will of the
<hi>Zephirus</hi>'s. Well, and what was the Iſſue of all this? Do you
think, that this Ignorant Age fell into a Conſultation, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Nature of
theſe Marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Spectacles? The People pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently believed, that they
were <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> who had gotten a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Air, there to
exerciſe their Conjurations, and to make it Hail upon their Corn-Fields. The
Learned Men, the Divines, and the Lawyers, were preſently of the ſame
Opinion with the Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Emperors alſo believed; and this Ridiculous
<hi>Chymaera</hi> got ſuch Credit amongſt All, that the Wiſe
<hi>Charlemaine,</hi> and after him <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Debonaire</hi>
inflicted grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous<pb n="175" facs="tcp:94889:92"/>Torments on all thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<hi>Tyrants</hi> of the <hi>Air.</hi> See this in the <hi>Firſt Chapter of
the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitularies</hi> of theſe two Emperors.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sylphs,</hi> ſeeing the People, the <hi>Pedants,</hi>
and the Crowned Heads alſo, thus taking up Arms againſt them, reſolved to
make them loſe this Evil Opinion, which they had of their Innocent Fleet; and
to manifeſt themſelves whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clearly to Men in all Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; to let
them ſee their Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Wives, their Common-Wealth, and their Government;
and then to come down into the Earth, in divers Parts of the World. They did,
as they had projected; and the People who ſaw theſe Men deſcend, remove
thither from all Places, already poſſeſſed with an Opinion, that they
were <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> who had left their Companions, to throw Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon upon
their Fruits, and into<pb n="176" facs="tcp:94889:93"/>their Wells: Being tranſported
with the Fury which Inſpired them with ſuch Imaginations, they dragged
theſe <hi>Innocents</hi> to Puniſhment. It is incredible, what a great
Number of them were made to ſuffer by Fire, and Water, over all this
Kingdom.</p>
               <p>It chanced one Day amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that at <hi>Lyons,</hi>
there was ſeen to deſcend from one of theſe Airy Ships, Three Men, and a
Woman: All the City gathered together about them; crying that they are
<hi>Magicians,</hi> and that <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaldus, the Duke of Bennevent,</hi> the
Enemy of <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> ſent them to deſtroy the Harveſt of the
<hi>French.</hi> The Four <hi>Innocents</hi> ſaid what they could, for their
Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; that they were of that Country; that they had but a little
while ſince, been carryed up into the Air by Miraculous Men, who had cauſed
them to ſee<pb n="177" facs="tcp:94889:93"/>unheard-of Wonders; and had intreated them to
give a Relation of them. The inraged People would not hear their Defence, but
went about to Burn them; when it happened, that the good Man, <hi>Agobard,</hi>
afterwards Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> who was a <hi>Monk</hi> in this City,
and having acquired a great Authority amongſt them, paſſing by, came to
appeaſe the Tumult: And after hearing the Peoples Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, and the
Defence of the Accuſed, gravely declared, that both one, and the other were
falſe: That theſe People had not deſcended down out of the Air; and that,
what the others affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have ſeen, was impoſſible.</p>
               <p>The People believing more what their good Father
<hi>Agobard,</hi> had ſaid, than their own Eyes, were Appeaſed, ſet at
Liberty the Four Ambaſſadors of the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> and received with
Admiration,<pb n="178" facs="tcp:94889:94"/>the Book which <hi>Agobard</hi> writ, for
Confirmation of the Sentence, which he had given: So the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the
Four Witneſſes, became invalid.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, they having eſcaped the Puniſhment, were
at Liberty to relate what they had ſeen; the which was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
without Fruit: For, if you well remember, that Age of <hi>Charlemaine</hi> was
very fruitful in <hi>Heroick</hi> Men: For it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured, that the
<hi>Woman,</hi> who had been amongſt the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> found Belief
amongſt the Ladies of that Time. So that, by the Grace of <hi>God,</hi> many
<hi>Sylphes</hi> were Immortalized: Many <hi>Sylphides</hi> alſo became
Immortal, by the Relation which theſe Three Men gave of their Beauty; which
thing induced the People of thoſe Times, to apply themſelves to
<hi>philoſophy,</hi> more than before. And<pb n="179" facs="tcp:94889:94"/>hence
proceeded all thoſe Stories of <hi>Fees,</hi> or <hi>Fairies,</hi> which you
find in the Amorous Legends of that Age of <hi>Charlemaine,</hi> and his
<hi>Court.</hi> All thoſe pretended <hi>Fees,</hi> were <hi>Sylphides</hi>
and <hi>Nymphs.</hi> Have you read theſe Stories of <hi>Heroes</hi> and
<hi>Fees?</hi> No, Sir, (ſaid I to him.)</p>
               <p>I am ſorry for it (continued he) for they would have given you
ſome <hi>Idea</hi> of the State, to which the <hi>Sages</hi> have reſolved
one day to reduce the World. Thoſe Heroick men, thoſe amours of the
<hi>Nimphs,</hi> thoſe journies to the Terreſtial Paradice, thoſe
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted Pallaces and Groves, and and all thoſe charming adventures which
there we read of, are but a little <hi>Idea</hi> of the life which the
<hi>Sages</hi> lead, and of what the World ſhall be, when they ſhall make
Wiſdom-raign therein. None ſhall be ſeen there but <hi>Heroes;</hi> the
meaneſt of our Children, ſhall<pb n="180" facs="tcp:94889:95"/>have the force of
<hi>Zoroaſter, Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius,</hi> or <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> and the
greateſt part of them, ſhall be accompliſhed as the Children which
<hi>Adam</hi> had had by <hi>Eve</hi> if he had not ſinned with her.</p>
               <p>Did you not tell me Sir (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted I) that God would not that
<hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> ſhould have had Children; that <hi>Adam</hi>
ſhould only have meddled with the <hi>Sylphides,</hi> and that <hi>Eve</hi>
ſhould not ſo much as think on any but the <hi>Sylphs,</hi> or the
<hi>Salamanders?</hi> 'Tis true (ſaid the Count) they ought not to have got
Children, by that way which they did. Does your <hi>Cabal</hi> then Sir
(continued I) teach ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention for Man and Woman to make Children
otherwiſe than by the ordinary Method? Yes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, does it (Anſwered
he). I beſeech you Sir (purſued I) do me the favour to teach it me. Hold,
Sir, you ſhall not know<pb n="181" facs="tcp:94889:95"/>that to day, an't pleaſe you.
(Said he to me ſmiling) I will revenge the People of the Elements, on you,
for having had ſo great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to undeceive you, of their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought
Devils. I doubt not but you are now come out of your Panick fears. I leave you
therefore, to give you leaſure to meditate, and deliberate before God, which
ſpecies of Elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubſtances, it will be prope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for his Glory,
and for yours, to make ſharer of your Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p>I ſhall go, in the mean time, to recollect my ſelf a little,
in order to the diſcourſe which you have put me upon making to the
<hi>Gnomes,</hi> to night. Do you go (ſaid I) do expound to them, ſome
Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Averroes.</hi> I believe (ſaid the Count) that from thence
might be drawn a very good ſubject; for I have a deſign to preach to 
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:94889:96"/>them of the excellence of Man, to induce them to ſeek
out for an alliance with us. And <hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> after <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
has held two things, which it would be well that I ſhould clear. The one is
of the nature of the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp; the other is of the <hi>Sovereign
Good.</hi> He ſays, that there is but one ſole Underſtanding Created,
which is the Image of the Uncre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated, and that this only Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
ſuffices for all men: This requires explanation. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the
Soveraign good, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verroes</hi> ſays, that it conſiſts in the
converſation of Angels; which is not <hi>Cabalistick</hi> enough. For Man
during this life, may, and is Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to enjoy God, as you will ere long
perceive; and as you will make tryal of, when you ſhall be in the Rank of the
<hi>Sages.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So ended the Diſcourſe with the Count of <hi>Gabalis.</hi>
He came<pb n="183" facs="tcp:94889:96"/>again the next morning, and brought me the Sermon
which he had made to the <hi>Subterranean</hi> People: 'Tis very marvellous! I
would give it you, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of the entertainment which a
<hi>Viſcounteſs</hi> and I had with this great Man, if I were ſure that
all my Readers had a right underſtanding, and would not take it ill, that I
ſhould divertiſe my ſelf at the expence of Fools. If I ſee that they
will oblige my Book, as much as it will do others; and that they do not do me
the unjuſtice to ſuſpect me, as though I would give credit to the
ſecret Sciences under pretence of making them Ridiculous; I may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue to
make my ſelf merry with the Count of <hi>Gabalis,</hi> and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly give
you another Tome.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="translators_observations">
            <pb facs="tcp:94889:97"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94889:97"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOR'S <hi>Animadverſions</hi> ON THE Foregoing
Diſcourſes.</head>
            <p>I Have ventur'd to Tranſlate, at my vacant Hours, (being much
affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the odd Curioſity of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſtick Sciences</hi>) this
Tract, ſomewhat reſembling a <hi>Philoſophick Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance,</hi> as Fabulous
and Weak, as an Old <hi>Monk's Legend.</hi> In it, you will find the
<hi>Cabaliſt</hi> to be a miſerable Blind Creature, fit for a Dog and a
Bell; yet in his own Conceit, more ſeeing than all the World, and beſt
qualifyed for the Office of a Guide: Much Devoted to idle Traditions; by which
crooked Line, he meaſures <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Reaſon:</hi> A great
Hater of <hi>Women;</hi> yet much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to Venery, in a
<hi>Philoſophick</hi> Way. In a word, A Creature of much<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94889:98"/>Choler, and little Brains. The Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him, may make you Laugh;
but his Folly, will ſometimes grieve you.</p>
            <p>I preſume, none but a <hi>French-Man,</hi> would at firſt,
have taken the pains to Collect, and give ſuch Credit to theſe
<hi>Cabaliſtick</hi> Whymſeys, as my <hi>Author</hi> ſeems to do: That
Nation being ſo Airy, and ſo Amorous, may boaſt it ſelf, if it
pleaſe, ſprung from the <hi>Sylphes,</hi> thoſe Brisk Inhabitants of the
Air, mentioned in this fore-going Treatiſe. I ſhall not envy them, if they
ſay, <hi>Pharamond,</hi> the Founder of their Kingdom, was Begot by the
Salamander <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> or any other of his Fiery Succeſſors; who
for his GLORY only, ſhall make offenſive Wars upon his peaceful Neighbors;
and whil'ſt he Lives, ſhall be the Incendiary of <hi>Europe,</hi> to gain
after Death, the Name of <hi>Nimrod,</hi> a <hi>Mighty Hunter:</hi> That
Nations may be ſaid, like <hi>Hares,</hi> to have fled before him. Yet, to
the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of an <hi>Engliſh-Man,</hi> the <hi>Greek</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians
tell us, That <hi>Xerxes,</hi> who ſayl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Continent, and walked
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Deep; who was ſo imprudent, as to whip <hi>Neptune,</hi> and to
bluſter with the <hi>North-Wind;</hi> was at laſt, eaſily 
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94889:98"/>beaten by the People; who truſted, by the Order of
Providence, in <hi>Wooden-Walls.</hi> But, as to this <hi>Cabaliſtick
Diſcourſe,</hi> which my <hi>French-Man</hi> has gathered for us, with
pretence of deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it; but indeed does not, to much purpoſe; ſeeming
rather, like ſome Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitual Lyar, by long Continuation in Falſhood, not to
obſerve it; It may not be unſit to anſwer its vain <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi>
from Authors; as it pretends to defend it ſelf, in abuſe of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heathen</hi> Writers, both <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and
<hi>Poets,</hi> never make mention, but of two Intellectual Beings, beſides
the Gods; <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Demi-Gods,</hi> and the Souls of <hi>Men.</hi>
The <hi>Semidei</hi> were always eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them Immortal, from the good
Pleaſure of <hi>Jupiter;</hi> whom <hi>Plato</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, ſpeaking to
them thus: <hi>Vos qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, Immortales eſſe non poteſtis, ſed mea
poteſtate Immortales critis. You indeed may be Mortal; but through my good
Pleaſure, you ſhall be Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal.</hi> As to the <hi>Souls of Men,</hi>
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon ſolid Reaſons, they could not deny their Immortality; and
ſince they were not able to underſtand the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of our future
State, they were<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94889:99"/>neceſſitated (not knowing how to
diſpoſe of the <hi>Souls of Men</hi> after Death) either to allow of
<hi>Pythagoras</hi> his <hi>Tranſmigra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which was a Marching of the
Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Tenant, from one Houſe to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after its Leaſe was expired:
Or elſe, according to <hi>Virgil,</hi> who had it from <hi>Plato,</hi> That
the <hi>Soul</hi> deſired to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate again, after its Purgation in the
<hi>Elizian Fields.</hi> 
               <q> Rurſus &amp; incipiunt in Corpora velle reverti.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But in all Ages, Speculative Men in their niceſt
<hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> could never be thought well in their Wits; who
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed the Exiſtence of <hi>Semi-homines, Half-Men,</hi> and
<hi>Women,</hi> that inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Elements, Creatures compounded of Material
Souls and Bodyes, Inferior, yet Superior to Man, in Faculties and Powers.
Strange Contradiction! That Beings, conſiſting only of Mater, ſhould act
impoſſibly againſt their Nature: Since Mater, according to the Axioms,
and Statute-Laws of all <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> whether <hi>Academicks,
Peripateticks, Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks,</hi> or <hi>Cynicks,</hi> is not able to act, or think
really. Now, to over-throw the Aſſertion of theſe <hi>Elementary
People</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94889:99"/>at once; and by undermining the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, to
deſtroy the Superſtructure: Let us conſider, what can be more Abſurd,
or Fallacious in <hi>Logick,</hi> and <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy,</hi> than to beg a
Principle of a Thing, that cannot be; and then to faſten a Concluſion, from
moſt Erroneous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. To propoſe a Creature, whoſe Eſſence and
Form is Mortal, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Material; Yet at the ſame time, to make
this Creature Divine in its Faculties, Acute in its Operations, and Superior to
Man in its <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either as to Divine, or Human Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; which
can proceed from nothing, but an Immortal, and Immaterial Cauſe. Let any
thinking Perſon judge, whether ſuch Notions do not more deſerve
<hi>Helli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore,</hi> to purge them, than Diſputation to confute them? And,
whether <hi>Bedlam</hi> be not the fitteſt <hi>Accademy,</hi> for the
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers?</p>
            <p>This <hi>Cabaliſtick</hi> Fancy, certainly in its Original,
ſeems exactly to mimick the Follies of the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> The Poets of old
feigned three <hi>Gods,</hi> to piſs in an Oxes Hide, to make the famous
<hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion:</hi> So the Ingredients of <hi>Arianiſm, Judaiſm,</hi> and
<hi>Ethuiciſm</hi> compoſed a<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94889:100"/>Religion obliging to the
Carnal <hi>Turk;</hi> Thus a Prophane Interpreter of the Old and New
Teſtament, with the falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of Heathen Philoſophy, ſoon
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate into a <hi>Cabaliſt.</hi> Sometimes the Venial Follies of many
paſſages Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Laughter in me; But I was grieved at the rambling
Prophanation of ſome places of Holy Scripture: 
<q>Pinge duos Angues Sacer eſt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. 
<bibl>Perſ.</bibl>
               </q>Amongſt others, as to his perverting
the ſence of <hi>Adams</hi> eating the Apple, to lying with his Wife. I will
grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if it be neceſſary, make Anſwer in the Orthodox words of St.
<hi>Auguſtine, De Civit: Dei. Lib. 14. Cap. 26. Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupante peecato,
exilium de Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſo ante meruerunt, quam in opere ferendae propaginis
tranquillo arbitrio convenirent. They firſt finned, and were baniſhed out
of Paradice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they attempted the propagation of poſterity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then if theſe Elementary People, by nature, are Good, Juſt,
Holy, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourers of God; How dare they rob him of his Honour, by permitting
the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it, to themſelves? as in this<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94889:100"/>ſtory,
amongſt other <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcholaſtick Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, of Hiſtory and Chronology.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> according to their Chymaeras, being
<hi>Prince</hi> of the People which inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit the <hi>Fire,</hi> had two
Children, by <hi>Veſta</hi> the Wife of <hi>Noah,</hi> viz.
<hi>Zoroaſter</hi> and <hi>Egeria Zoroaſter</hi> a great <hi>Hero,</hi> and
the <hi>Inventer of Magick is reported by Juſtin</hi> to have been
<hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Bactri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> yet was overcome by <hi>Ninus,</hi>
for all his magick and valour, living after this computation about the end of
<hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> Life. Now, how doe the <hi>Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> know,
<hi>Noahs</hi> Wife, (ſuppoſing her name was <hi>Veſta</hi>) not to be
dead before her Son <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> was Born; and if <hi>Juſtin</hi>
miſtakes, as 'tis very probable, <hi>he may,</hi> and calls him
<hi>Zoroaſter,</hi> whom <hi>Cteſias</hi> calls <hi>Oxiartes King</hi> of
the <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trians:</hi> For <hi>Pliny</hi> doubts very much, whither magick be
of ſo long a ſtanding, and if <hi>Xanthus the Lydian</hi> a very An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
writer reckons but 600. Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> and
<hi>Xerxes;</hi> Then <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roaſter</hi> muſt live an Hundred Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the
<hi>Wars of Troy,</hi> and our <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> muſt look for another
<hi>Hero,</hi> or elſe conclude the Son to be Born 800. Years after
<hi>Noah's</hi> Wife was dead, preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94889:101"/>ſhe lived
as long as <hi>Noah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, How could <hi>Egeria</hi> the Daughter, mentioned to be
Born in the Ark, Live till the time of <hi>Numa Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius,</hi> whoſe
miſtreſs ſhe was, though very old, of about 1600 Years ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>For is it reaſonable, that ſhe ſhould laſt out ſo long?
ſince the Ofſpring of theſe <hi>Elementary</hi> People being Men and
Women, and of mixt ſubſtances muſt not unproportionably exceed the Common
life of Man. For <hi>Rome</hi> was built a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 1194. Years after the Death of
<hi>Noah;</hi> Therefore I would always ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe <hi>Romantick</hi> and
<hi>Cabaliſtick</hi> Writers, if they would have Fables paſs ſmoothly, to
avoid groſs abſurdities in Hiſtory and Chronology: Beſides, according
to them, this <hi>Egeria</hi> impiouſly inſtructed her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, (contrary to
the pretended deſire, or piety of the <hi>Elementary</hi> People) to
Worſhip her Father <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> under the Type of the <hi>Veſtal
Fire.</hi> Thus you ſee how all things of Divinity and Humanity are made a
<hi>Chaos.</hi>
            </p>
            <q> 
               <l>—Congeſtaque eodem</l> 
               <l>Non bene junctarum diſcordia ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na rerum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94889:101"/>As to the Oracles, where my Author ſeems
moſt pleaſed: 'Tis very eaſy to prove, who inſpired them, but I will
confute the <hi>Cabaliſt,</hi> from <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> becauſe he affects
him ſo much. He lays down in the preceding book for a maxim; That the Devil
is not at Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to ramble at his pleaſure; nor could it be he, that
ſpake in Oracles; for he never would ſay any thing againſt his own
Intereſt, as he muſt, if it were the Devil that pronounced them; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
that the Oracle muſt be ſpoke by ſome one of the <hi>Elementary</hi>
People, who, knowing God, ſpake ſo reverently of him. To this I propoſe
but one Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle out of <hi>Porphyrius;</hi> and if he will grant any of the
<hi>Elementary</hi> People to ſpeak it, I am ſatisfied, and muſt
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them, (if he can prove their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) to be worſe than Devils.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Porphyrius</hi> in his Book
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſays that enquiring of
<hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> to what Deity he ſhould Sacrifice, for the reducing of his
Wife from Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; The <hi>Daemon</hi> anſwered in Greek Verſe,
according to this ſence. 
<q>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:94889:102"/>You may ſooner write upon the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or
by ſtretching out your Wings, Fly like a Bird through the Air, than recover
the ſences of your wicked Wife, once pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted after that manner. Let her go
where ſhe pleaſes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering in her empty fallacies, ſinging Hymns
to her Crucified God, with moſt vain lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whom upright Judges
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and an Ignominious Death deſtroyed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I will not pretend, in this place, to med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le with this Curſed <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> ſince St.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> has done it ſo fully for me already in this caſe.
<hi>De Civ. Dei. Lib. 19. Cap. 23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if the Devil ſpake here, the <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> is undone,
and if a <hi>Sylph</hi> ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered this, he is as much Gravelled, therefore
according to his own precari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſuppoſition, let him avoid the
<hi>Dilem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> if he can.</p>
            <p>I will detain the Reader no longer, only let him as he reads this,
or any piece of this kind, both laugh and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, at the extravagant
boldneſs of<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94889:102"/>Mans imagination, and think in what danger of
Shipwrack, that Veſſel is, which has too much Sail and too little
Ballaſt. Laſtly, That the ſafeſt way in Divine and Humane
ſpeculations will be to try all things, at GODS SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CRED ORACLES, which make a
Man the beſt Philoſopher, and beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
            <q> 
               <l>—Exemplaria Sacra</l> 
               <l>Nocturna verſate manu, verſate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urna.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:94889:103"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 6. line 23. read <hi>Devoto.</hi> p. 8. l. 24. r. <hi>German
Lord.</hi> p. 10. l. 20. r. <hi>in of a moſt.</hi> p. 40. l. ult. r.
<hi>Theophraſtus Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſt.</hi> p. 43. l. 4. for <hi>which</hi> r.
<hi>whom.</hi> p. 42. l. 8. for <hi>of this Judgment</hi> r. <hi>in this
Point.</hi> p. 85. l. 5. r. <hi>unpowerful exhalation.</hi> ibid. l. 19. r.
<hi>Man.</hi> p. 88. l. 3. r. <hi>his Folly.</hi> p. 92. l. 17.
<hi>Daimonas.</hi> p. 95. l. 16. for <hi>ſeen</hi> r. <hi>heard of.</hi> p.
96. r. <hi>Rodrigo.</hi> p. 114. r. <hi>the one &amp; twentyeth Chap.</hi> p.
115. l. 22. for <hi>Loyns</hi> r. <hi>Loves.</hi> p. 116. r. <hi>Numa
Pompilius. Tranſlat. Animadv.</hi> pag. 2. lin. 27. for <hi>Imprudent</hi>
read <hi>Impudent.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94889:103"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
